<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe description of the whole worlde wherein are particularly described all the monarchies, empires, and kingdomes of the same, with their seuerall titles and situations thereunto adioyning.</title>
            <author>Abbot, George, 1562-1633.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23379030</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23379030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26616</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26616)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1826:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe description of the whole worlde wherein are particularly described all the monarchies, empires, and kingdomes of the same, with their seuerall titles and situations thereunto adioyning.</title>
                  <author>Abbot, George, 1562-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[63] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Iudson, for Iohn Browne, and are to be sould at the signe of the Bible in Fleete-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to George Abbot by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Geography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE DESCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE whole worlde.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN ARE PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly deſcribed all the Monarchies, Empires, and kingdomes of the ſame: with their ſeuerall titles and ſituations thereunto adioyning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Iudſon,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Browne,</hi> and are to be ſould at the ſigne of the Bible in Fleete-ſtreete. 1599.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26616:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE DESCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE WHOLE WORLD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He globe of the earth, doth eyther ſhewe the ſea, or land. The ſea generall is called by the name of the OCEAN, which coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth all the world, and taketh his name in ſpeciall, eyther of the place neere which it commeth: as <hi>Oceanus Britannicus: Mare Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus: Sinus Perſicus: Mare Atlanticum,</hi> of the hill Atlas in the Weſt-part of Africke: or of the finder out: as <hi>Fretum Magelanicum:</hi> or of ſome other accident, as the Red ſea, becauſe the ſand is red: <hi>Mare Mediterraneum:</hi> becauſe it runneth betweene the landes of Europe, and Afrike: <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Icarium,</hi> becauſe Icarus was drowned there, or the like. There be ſome few ſeas which haue no entercourſe with the OCEAN, as <hi>Mare mortuum</hi> neare Paleſtina: <hi>Mare Caſpium, ſiue Hircanum,</hi> not farre from Armenia, and ſuch a one is ſaid to be in the North part of America.</p>
            <p>The Straites or narrow ſeas are noted in the Latine, by the name of <hi>Fretum:</hi> as, <hi>Fretum Britanicum,</hi> the Engliſh narrowe ſeas, <hi>Fretum Herculeum,</hi> the ſtraightes betweene Barbarie and Spaine, <hi>Fretum Magellanicum. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The earth is either Ilands, which are thoſe that are who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compaſſed by the ſea, as <hi>Britannia, Sicilia, Corſica:</hi> or the continent which is called in the Engliſh, the firme lande,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:4"/>in the Latine <hi>Continent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The olde knowne firme land was conteined onely in Aſia, Europe, and Africa, Europe is deuided from Africa by the <hi>Mediterran ſea,</hi> and from Aſia by the riuer Tanais, whereby appeareth that the North-partes of Aſia, and of Europe in olde time were but little knowne, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            <p>Africa is deuided from Europe by the <hi>Mediterran ſea,</hi> from Aſia by the riuer Nilus: and ſo Aſia, by Tanais and Nilus, is ſeuered from Europe and Afrike.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Hiſpania.</head>
               <p>TO ſay nothing of England and Ireland, the moſt we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne countrie of Europe is Spaine: which is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on the South wth the <hi>Mediterran ſea,</hi> on the Weſt with the <hi>Atlantike,</hi> on the North with the <hi>Oceanus Cantabricus</hi> or the Spaniſh ſeas, on the Eaſt, with France, from which it is ſeuered with certaine mountaines, called <hi>Montes Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renei,</hi> or the Pyrenei hills.</p>
               <p>In this countrie heretofore there were many kingdoms: as the kingdome of Portingale toward the Weſt, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Granada toward the South, the kingdome of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre and Aragon towarde the Eaſt, and the kingdome of Caſtile in the middle of the land: but the whole dominion is now vnder the king of Spaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Gallia.</head>
               <p>THe next countrie is France: which is bounded on the Weſt with the Pyrenei hills: on the North with the Engliſh ſeas: on the Eaſt with Germanie: on the South-eaſt
<pb facs="tcp:26616:4"/>with the Alpe-hilles: on the South-weſt with the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterran ſea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was in auncient time deuided into three partes: <hi>Aquitania</hi> which is toward the Weſt: <hi>Celtica</hi> toward the North, and Weſt: and <hi>Belgica</hi> which is toward the North. <hi>Belgica</hi> is ſome times called <hi>Gallia inferior,</hi> and ſometime <hi>Germania inferior:</hi> but we call it commonly by the name of the Lowe countries: the gouernement where of at this day is not at all vnder France: but <hi>Gallia Celtica</hi> and <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania</hi> are vnder the French king.</p>
               <p>France hath many petie gouernements that doe bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vpon it: as the Duke of Sauoie, the State of the Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, the Dukedome of Loraine, the Burgundians or Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons: againſt all which, the King is forted to keepe his fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier townes.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more famous in this kingdome then the Salike lawe: whereby it is prouided; that no woman. nor the heire of her, as in her right, ſhall enioy the crowne of France a but it goeth alwayes to the heire male.</p>
               <p>The Switzers are a people called in olde time <hi>Heluetij.</hi> who haue no Noblemen or Gentlemen among them, but onely the citizens of their townes: the yearely officers whereof, and their councill, doe gouerne their State.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Germania,</head>
               <p>THe next countrie vnto France, on the Eaſt-ſide, is <hi>Germanie,</hi> which is bounded on the Weſt with France, and the Lowe countries: on the North with Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, and the Daniſh ſeas: on the Eaſt with Pruſſia, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia, and Hungarie: on the South-eaſt with Iſtris, and Illyricum: on the South with the Alpe-hilles &amp; with Italy.</p>
               <p>The gouernour generall of this countrie is balled the
<pb facs="tcp:26616:5"/>Emperour of Germanie; who is choſen by three ſpirituall princes, the Archbiſhop of Colen called <hi>Colonienſis;</hi> the Archbiſhop of Ments called <hi>Moguntinus;</hi> and the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Triers called <hi>Treuereuſis:</hi> and three temporal prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the Duke of Saxonie; the Marques of Brandeburg; and the Countie Palantine of Rhine: which if they cannot agree, as to make a <hi>Maior</hi> parte in their election: then the king of Boheme hath alſo a voyce: whereof it commeth to to be ſaide, that there bee ſeuen Princes electors of the Empire.</p>
               <p>There is not that free libertie of chooſing the Emperour out of any countrie, as was heretofore. But the election is tyed, within one hundred yeares vnto the houſe of Auſtria, and at this day of of them, the king of Bohemia is Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who is called Rodulphus. 2.</p>
               <p>Bohemia is a kingdome in the middle of Germanie, which is compaſſed rounde with a mightie wood, called <hi>Silua Hirciniae:</hi> The chiefe citie thereof is called Prage.</p>
               <p>In Germanie all are at a kinde of commaundement of the Emperour: but moſt of the Princes (otherwiſe) take on them as abſolute gouernours in their dominion. So that they haue libertie of religion, they make lawes, they raiſe ſouldiers, they ſtampe money with their owne coyne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as abſolute princes. So doth the Duke of Saxonie, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and the reſt.</p>
               <p>There are alſo free States and cities; which haue the ſame authoritie, as Argentine, Frankford, and other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Italia.</head>
               <p>ON the South-ſide of the Alpes (and Germanie lyeth Italie, ſtretching it ſelfe out in length towarde the South, and Eaſt. It hath on the South-ſide the Iland Sicilia:
<pb facs="tcp:26616:5"/>on the Eaſt, that part of the <hi>Med.</hi> which is called <hi>Mare A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driaticum,</hi> or <hi>Mare ſuperum;</hi> which ſeuereth Italie from Graecia: on the Weſt ſide, that part of the <hi>Med.</hi> which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mare Tyrrhenum,</hi> or <hi>Mare inferum:</hi> and by ſome <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Liguſticum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This countrie for the figure thereof, is by ſome likened vnto a long leafe of a tree: it hath in the middle of it which goeth all in length, a mightie mountaine, named <hi>Mons Aperminus,</hi> which is likened to the <hi>Spina</hi> or ridge-bone of the backe: out of this hill ſpring diuers Riuers, which runne on both ſides of it, into the <hi>Adriatike,</hi> and <hi>Tyrrhene, or Tuſcane</hi> ſeas.</p>
               <p>The North parte of this Italie is that which in auncient time was called <hi>Gallia Comata,</hi> or <hi>Gallia Ciſalpina,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gallia.</note> inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then by the French-men. It is now called <hi>Longobardia,</hi> or Lombardie, wherein ſtand many rich gouernements: as the Dukedome of Millaine, of Mantua, of Florence, and others. It is for the pleaſantneſſe thereof, in reſpect of the ſoile, aire, waters, and great varietie of wines, and fruites, likened now by ſome to Paradiſe, or the garden of God.</p>
               <p>In this Italy, which was heretofore one intire gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the floriſhing eſtate of the Romanes, are now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abſolute States, and princedomes, by the great policie of the Biſhop of Rome: who thought it the beſt way to make himſelfe great, to weaken the Empire. So he hath not onely driuen the Emperour out of all Italie into Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie: but hath diminiſhed his Maieſtie in both: by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo many petie gouernments, which hold themſelues ſoueraigne rulers, without relation to any other.</p>
               <p>As there are many States in Italie, ſo one of the chiefeſt are the Venicians called <hi>Reſp. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetorum,</hi> or the State of Venice: becauſe they are not gouerned by any one: but by their Senate, &amp; gentlemen, although they haue a duke: with whoſe ſtampe their money is coyned, and in whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:26616:6"/>name all their executions of iuſtice are done. But this duke is euery way limited by the State.</p>
               <p>This Citie of Venice ſtandeth in an <hi>Aeſtuarium</hi> or ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of earth in the North-part of the <hi>Adriatike</hi> ſea, ſo ſafely, that it is held inuincible. There is in it but one ſtreete of firme land: into the other the ſea doth flow at euerie tide. They haue beene a great and rich State; not onely poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing much in Italie, as Padua their Vniuerſitie, and other things which nowe they doe: but a great part of Illyricum and many rich Ilands in the <hi>Med.</hi> as Candie, called com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Creta, Cyprus, Zacynthus, and other.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The impoueriſhing of their ſtate, hath partly beene by the encroching of the Turke: but eſpecially By the decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that trafique which they had to Alexandria in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt for their ſpices, and other riches of Perſia. Arabia, and the Eaſt Indies. Since the courſe of the Portugals, to thoſe Eaſterne countries hath beene by ſea, by the backeſide of Africa.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Here ſtandeth the Citle of Florence, a renowmed Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Lombardie, which is gouerned by a Duke, an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Prince. This Dukedome is in the familie of the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> from whom came <hi>Katherine de Medices,</hi> the wife of Henrie the 2. King of France lately ſo well knowne by the name of Queene mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In this Lombardie ſtandeth alſo the Dukedome of Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, a moſt rich and pleaſant thing, which ſometime had beene gouerned by a Duke of their owne: but of late hath beene poſſeſſed by the Spaniard, and ſometime by the French, and is now in the gouernment and poſſeſſion of the king of Spaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> A good part of Italie is vnder the Biſhop of Rome, which commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly is called the land of the Church: where the Pope is a Prince abſolute: not onely ſpirituall, as elſe-where hee claimeth: but alſo temporall: making lawes, requiring tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:6"/>raiſing ſouldiers, and executing iuſtice as a Monarche.</p>
               <p>In the South part of Italie lieth the kingdome of Naples, which is a countrie very rich, and full of all kind of pleaſure, aboundant in Nobilitie; whereof commeth to bee ſaid that prouerbe: Naples for Nobilitie, Rome for religion, Millaine for beautie, Florence for policie, and Venice for riches.</p>
               <p>This was heretofore ruled by a king <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>r owne, till the time of Ioane Queene of Naples, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y deede of gift, did firſt graunt that kingdome to the Kings of Aragon in Spaine: and afterward by will (with a reuocation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,) did bequeath it to the houſe of Anioy in France. Since which time the kingdome of Naples hath ſometimes beene in the hand of the Spaniard, ſometimes poſſeſſed by the French, and is now vnder the King of Spaine: vnto this is annexed alſo the Dukedome of Calabria.</p>
               <p>There be moreouer in Italie many other Prince-domes and States; as the Dukedome of Ferrara; the Dukedome of Mantua; the Dukedome of Vrbine; the Dukedome of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, &amp; Placentia: the State of Luca: the State of Genua, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Genowaies, which are gouerned by their Senate: but haue a Duke as they haue at Venice. There bee alſo ſome other, by which meanes, the glory and ſtrength of Italy is decayed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Dania, Suecia, &amp; Noruegia.</head>
               <p>AS Italie lieth on the Southſide of Germanie, ſo Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke lieth on the North, into the middle of which land the ſea breaketh in by a place called <hi>the Sound.</hi> The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſte of which paſſage bringeth great riches, as an ordinarie tribute to the King of Denmarke: this is a kingdome, and ruled by an abſolute gouernour.</p>
               <p>On the North and Eaſt ſide of Denmarke lieth Suecia, commonly called Sweden or Swethen: which is alſo a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:26616:7"/>of it ſelfe. Where the King profeſſeth himſelfe to bee <hi>Rex Suecorum, Gothorum, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andalorum.</hi> Wherby we may know that the Gothes and Vandales which in times paſt did waſte Italie, and other Nations of Chriſtendome, did come out of this country.</p>
               <p>On the Northſide and Weſt of Sweden lieth Noruegia or Norway, which is at this day vnder the gouernement of the King of Denmarke, although heretofore it hath beene a free kingdome of it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Within the Sounde, on the Eaſt part of the ſea, lieth Dantzicke: where are three townes of Hanſe-men, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, and allies vnto the King of Denmarke.</p>
               <p>There is no great thing to be noted in theſe countries: but that from Denmarke commeth much come to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of other parts of Chriſtendome: and that from all theſe countries is brought great furniture for warre, or for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. As maſts, cables, ſteele, fadles, armour, gunpowder, &amp; the like. And that in the ſeas adioyning to theſe parts, there are fiſhes of much more monſtrous ſhape, then elſe-where are to be found: The people of theſe countries are by their profeſſion, Lutherans for religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Ruſsia, ſiue Moſcouia.</head>
               <p>ON the Eaſt ſide of Sweden beginneth the dominion of the Emperour of Ruſſia (although Ruſſia, or Moſcouia it ſelf doth lie ſome what more into the Eaſt) which is a great and mightie Monarchie, extending it ſelfe euen from Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Finmarke, many a thouſand mile in length vnto the <hi>Caſpian ſea:</hi> ſo that it containeth in it a great part of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, and much of Aſia alſo.</p>
               <p>The gouernour there calleth himſelfe Emperour of Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, great Duke of Moſconia, with many other titles of Princedomes, and Cities, whoſe dominion was very much
<pb facs="tcp:26616:7"/>enlarged by the Emperour not long ſince dead: whome in Ruſſie they call <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an VaſilIwich,</hi> in the Latine <hi>Iohannes Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des:</hi> who raigning long, and being fortunate in warre, did very much enlarge this mightie dominion.</p>
               <p>The people of this countrie are rude, and vnlearned, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuperſtitious, a kinde of Chriſtians: but rather following the Greeke Church. Their buildings is moſt of wood, euen in their chiefe Citie of Moſco: inſomuch, that the Tartars wholy in the North-eaſt of them breaking oft into their countries, euen vnto the very Citie of Moſco, doe ſet fire on their Cities, which by reaſon of their woodden buildings, are quickly deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>The paſſage by ſea into this countrie (which was wont to be through the Sound, and ſo afterward by land) was firſt diſcouered by the Engliſh: who with great danger of the frozen ſeas, did firſt aduenture to ſaile ſo far North, as to compaſſe Lapland, Finmarke, Scrikfinia, and Biarmia: and ſo paſſing to the Eaſt by Noua Zimbla, halfe the way almoſt to Cathaio, haue entred the riuer called <hi>Duina:</hi> by which they diſperſe themſelues for marchandize both by water &amp; land, into the moſt parts of the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Emperour.</p>
               <p>This Empire is at this day one of the greateſt dominions in the world: both for compaſſe of grounde, and for multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of men: ſauing that it lyeth far North, and ſo yeeldeth not pleaſure or good trafique, with many other of the beſt nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Pruſia, &amp; Polonia.</head>
               <p>IN Europe, on the Eaſt and North corner of Germany lyeth a countrie called Pruſſia, in Latine moſt times <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſſia,</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Pruthen,</hi> or <hi>Spruſa:</hi> of whome, little is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, ſauing that they be gouerned by one, in a kinde of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of religion, whome they call the Grand-maſter: and that they are a meanes to keepe the Moſcouite &amp; the Turke from ſome other partes of Chriſtendome.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:8"/>
               <p>On the Eaſt-ſide of Germanie, betweene Ruſſia &amp; Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, lyeth Polonia, or Poland, which is a kingdome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from other of Europe: becauſe the king there is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by election by ſome of the Princes neare adioyning, as was lately Henry the third, King of France. Theſe electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons oftentimes doe make great factions there; ſo that inta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king partes, they grow often there into ciuill warre.</p>
               <p>The king of Polonia is almoſt continually in warre, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Moſcouite, who lyeth in the Eaſt and North-eaſt of him; or with the Turke, who lyeth on the South and South-eaſt; and ſometimes alſo with the Princes of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; whereupon the Poles doe commonly deſire to chuſe warriors to their King.</p>
               <p>In this countrie are none but Chriſtians; but ſo, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of all religions is permitted, inſomuch, that there be Papiſts, Colleges of Ieſuites, both of Lutherans, and Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes opinions, Anabaptiſts, Artians, and diuers others. This is that countrie, which in times paſt was called Sarmatia, the chiefe citie whereof is named Cracouia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Hungaria, &amp; Auſtria.</head>
               <p>ON the South-ſide of Germanie lyeth Hungarie, called in the Latine <hi>Pannonia;</hi> which haue bene heretofore deuided into <hi>Pannonia ſuperior,</hi> and <hi>Pannonia inferiore</hi> it is an abſolute kingdome, and hath heretofore bene ritch and populous. The Chriſtians that doe liue there, haue among them diuers ſortes of religions, as in Poland. The kingdome hath bene a great obſtacle againſt the Tuckes comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtendome: but eſpecially in the time of Iohannes Huniades, who did mightily with many great victories re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe the Turke. Here ſtandeth <hi>Buda,</hi> which was hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great fortreſſe of Chriſtendome. But the glory of this kingdome is almoſt vtterly decayed, by reaſon that the Turke, who partly by policle and partly by force, doth now poſſeſſe the greateſt parte of it. So that the people are fled
<pb facs="tcp:26616:8"/>from thence, and the Chriſtians which remaine there are in miſerable ſeruitude: Notwithſtanding, ſome part of <hi>Panno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſuperior</hi> doth yet belong to Chriſtendome.</p>
               <p>That corner of Germanie which lieth neereſt to Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is called <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which is an Archdukedome. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which houſe are come many of the Princes of Germany, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of Europe: ſo that the Crowne imperiall of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie is now tied to ſome one of this houſe.</p>
               <p>In this countrie ſtandeth <hi>Vienna</hi> that noble citie, which is now the principall bulwarke of all Chriſtendome againſt the Turke: from whence Soliman was repelled by Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandus King of Hungarie, in the time of the Emperour Charles the fift. It was in this country, that Richard the firſt, king of <hi>England,</hi> in his returne from the holy land, was taken priſoner by the Archduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and ſo put to a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous raunſome. The Archduke that now is, by the King of Spaine, is appointed in the place of the Duke of Parma, as gouernour of the low countries. Through both <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Hungarie</hi> doth runne the mightie riuer <hi>Danubius,</hi> as through <hi>Germanie</hi> doth runne the <hi>Rhene,</hi> whereon groweth <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inum Rhen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um,</hi> commonly called Rheniſh wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Graecia.</head>
               <p>ON the South-ſide of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and South-eaſt, lyeth a countrie of Europe called in old time <hi>Dacia,</hi> which is large and wide, comprehending in it <hi>Tranſyluania, Valachia, Moldauia,</hi> and <hi>Seruia.</hi> Of which little is famous, ſaue that the men are warlike, and can hardly be brought to obedience, They haue lately bin vnder the King of Hungarie. The riuer <hi>Danubius</hi> doth diuide this <hi>Dacia</hi> from <hi>Myſia,</hi> commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> which lieth on the South from <hi>Danubius,</hi> and is ſeuered from <hi>Graecia</hi> by the mountaine <hi>Hamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Hamus</hi> towards the South lieth <hi>Graecia,</hi> bounded on the Weſt by the <hi>Adriatike ſea:</hi> on the Eaſt, by the <hi>Thracian ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Mare Aegeum:</hi> on the South, by the maine <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran
<pb facs="tcp:26616:9"/>ſea.</hi> This contained in old time foure ſpeciall parts: <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loponneſus, Achaia Macedonia,</hi> and <hi>Epirus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> which is now called <hi>Morea,</hi> is the South part of <hi>Graecia,</hi> being <hi>Paeninſula,</hi> or almoſt an Iland: for that it is ioyned by a litle ſtraight called <hi>Iſthmos,</hi> vnto the reſt of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</hi> Herein ſtood <hi>Sparta,</hi> and the auncient ſtate of <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> On the <hi>Iſthmos</hi> or ſtraight, ſtood the famous citie of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> which was in old time called the key of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the Weſt ſide of <hi>Graecia,</hi> next to <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> ſtood the kingdom of <hi>Macedonia:</hi> ſo famous vnder Philip for conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring al <hi>Graecia:</hi> and vnder Alexander, for vanquiſhing almoſt al the Eaſterne world: and for taking of the Monarchy from the Perſians: and remouing it to the Macedonians.</p>
               <p>On the North-ſide of <hi>Macedonia</hi> being the North-weſt from <hi>Graecia</hi> ſtood the little kingdome of <hi>Epirus:</hi> where raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Scanderbeg, which was in his time ſo great a ſcourge to the Turke.</p>
               <p>The reſt of <hi>Graecia</hi> was called <hi>Achaia,</hi> hauing on the North and Eaſt part thereof <hi>Thracia,</hi> on the North <hi>Haemus</hi> the hill on the Weſt <hi>Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Epirus,</hi> on the South <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> on the Eaſt thoſe ſeas which diuide <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe from <hi>Graecia.</hi> In this part ſtood <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> to the which S. Paule wrote his Epiſtle; and <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Thebes,</hi> and all the Cities of Boetia, and the Cities of the <hi>Achai, Argos, Elis,</hi> and many other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Macedonia</hi> is by the beſt Writers and by auncient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription rather ſound to ſtand on the North-ſide of <hi>Achaia,</hi> neere to the hill <hi>Hamus,</hi> and to <hi>Thracia,</hi> though ſome in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance haue taught the contrarie.</p>
               <p>In this countrie of <hi>Graecia</hi> were in auncient time manie Kingdoms and States, as at this day there are in <hi>Italie:</hi> as the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> the kingdome of <hi>Epyrus,</hi> the State of <hi>Athens,</hi> the gouernment of <hi>Sparta,</hi> the citie of <hi>Thebes,</hi> and very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places: in ſo much that almoſt euery towne had a peculiar gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But now it is all vnder one Monarchy.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:9"/>
               <p>From <hi>Graecia,</hi> in olde time, did almoſt all famous things come. Theſe were they that made the warre againſt <hi>Troy;</hi> that reſiſted Xerxes the mightie king of <hi>Perſia;</hi> that had the famous Law-makers; as Solon in <hi>Athens,</hi> and Licurgus in <hi>Lacedaemon;</hi> that tooke away the Monarchie from the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> that brought forth the famous Captaines, as Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Miltiades, Alexander, and many other that were the authours of ciuilitie vnto the Weſterne nations, and to ſome in the Eaſt; as <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, that gaue to Italie and to the Romanes the firſt light of learning: becauſe from them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe the firſt Poets, as Homer, Heſiodus, Sophocles, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other; the great Philoſophers, namely, Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle, and all the Sects of the Academicks, Stoicks, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticks, Epicureans, and almoſt all their ſchollers; the great Oratours, Demoſthenes, and Eſchines, and in one worde (the Mathematiks excepted, which came rather from the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi>) the whole flower of Artes and good learning.</p>
               <p>On the North eaſt part of <hi>Graecia</hi> ſtandeth <hi>Thracia,</hi> which though heretofore it hath beene diſtinguiſhed, yet now it is accounted as the chiefe part of <hi>Greece.</hi> Heere on the edge of the ſea-coaſt, verie neete vnto <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſtandeth the citie called <hi>Bizantium:</hi> but ſince <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> becauſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the great did new build it, and made it an imperiall citie. This was the chiefe reſidence of the Emperour of <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> ſometimes called new <hi>Rome,</hi> and the glorie of the Eaſt; where the generell Councell was once aſſembled: and one of the ſeas of the Patriarkes: who was called the Patriarke of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But by the great diſcord of the Chriſtians, all <hi>Graecia,</hi> and this City is fallen into the hands of the Turke: who nowe maketh it his place of imperiall abode. It was wonne in the time of Conſtantine the laſt Emperour: ſo that by Conſtantine it obtained his honour, and by Conſtantine it loſt it. In this citie lieth reſident with the Turke an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador or Agent for the Queene of England. The Chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:26616:10"/>that doe liue now in <hi>Gracia</hi> are in miſerable ſeruitude vnto the Turke. They diſagree in many things from the doctrine of the Church of Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Mari Europam &amp; Aſiam interiacente.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaide before, that on the North-part betweene <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> the riuer <hi>Tanais</hi> doth runne as a bounde of them both.</p>
               <p>This riuer runneth into a Lake called <hi>Maeotis palus,</hi> which bordereth on the confines of <hi>Scythia,</hi> or <hi>Tartaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Maeotis</hi> doth disburden it ſelfe into a wide ſea cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pontus Euxinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the mouth of this ſea, is a verie great ſtraight, knowne by the name of <hi>Thracius Boſphorus,</hi> where the breadth of the ſea is not aboue one mile, ſeuering <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe.</hi> On the ſide of Europe ſtandeth Conſtantinople: on the ſide of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, a Citie called Pera, which for the neareneſſe, is by ſome reckoned a part of Conſtantinople.</p>
               <p>After this ſtraight, the ſea openeth it ſelfe more large towarde the South: and is called by the name of <hi>Propontus.</hi> But then it goo weth again into another ſtraight, which they write to bee in bredth about two miles. This is called <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſpontus,</hi> hauing on the one ſide Abidus in Aſia, and on the other ſide Ceſtus, on the ſide of Europe.</p>
               <p>This is that place, where Xerxes the great King of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia did make his bridge ouer the ſea: ſo much renowmed in auncient hyſtories, which was not impoſſible, by reaſon of the narrowneſſe: the foundation of his bridge being reſted on ſhips. Here alſo may appeare the reaſon of that ſtorie of Leander and Hero: which Leander, is reported for the loue of her, to haue oftentimes ſwoom ouer the ſea, till at laſt he was drowned.</p>
               <p>From this ſtrait Southward, the ſea groweth more wide,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:10"/>and is called afterwardes by the name of <hi>Mare aege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and ſo diſcendeth vnto the full <hi>Mediterran.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Aſia, &amp; primo de Tartaria.</head>
               <p>ON the North-ſide of Aſia, ioyning vnto the dominion of the Emperour of Ruſſia: is Tartaria, in auntient time called Scythia: the bounds whereof did then extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into a good parte of Europe, and thereof was called Scythia Europhaea; but the greateſt parte of it lyeth in Aſia; A mightie large countrie, extending it ſelfe from the North to the vttermoſt ſea. On the Eaſt, to the dominion of the great <hi>Cham,</hi> or Prince of Cathaio, on the South, downe to the <hi>Mare Caſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Tartarians which nowe inhabite it, are men of great ſtature, rude of behauiour, no Chriſtians, but Gentiles: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe they acknowledge <hi>Mahomet.</hi> They haue ſewe or no Cities among them: but after the manner of the olde Seythians, doe liue in wilderneſſes: lying vnder their cartes, and following their droaues of cattell, by the milke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they doe nouriſh themſelues. They ſowe no come at all, becauſe they abide not long in any one place: but taking their direction from the North-pole-ſtarre, they remooue from one coaſt of their countrie vnto an other.</p>
               <p>The countrie is populous: and the men are great warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors: ſighting alwayes on horſebacke with their bowe and arrowes, and a ſhort ſworde. They haue among them infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſtore of horſes: whereof they ſell many vnto the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries adioyning. Their ordinarie foode in their warres, is horſefleſh, which they vſe to eate rawe, being chaſed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle by hanging at their ſaddle.</p>
               <p>They haue great warres with the countries adioyning: but eſpecially with the Moſcouite, and ſometimes with the Turke. From hence came <hi>Tamberlano,</hi> who brought ſeuen hundreth thouſands of the Tartarians at once into the fielde: wherein he diſtreſſed and tooke priſoner, <hi>Baiazet</hi> the great
<pb facs="tcp:26616:11"/>Turke; whome he afterwardes forced to feede as a dogge vnder his table. They haue now among them, many prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and gouernours, as thoſe haue one, whome they call the <hi>Crim Tartars:</hi> and thoſe haue another, which are the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> of <hi>Nagaia,</hi> and ſo diuers other.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh haue laboured to their great expences, to finde out the way by the North Seas of <hi>Tartaria,</hi> to goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Cathaio</hi> and <hi>China.</hi> But by reaſon of the frozen ſeas, they haue not yet preuailed. Although it be now reported, that the Flemmings haue diſcouered that paſſage: which is like to be to the great benefite of the Northeme partes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Cathaio, &amp; China.</head>
               <p>NExt beyond <hi>Tartaria</hi> on the North-eaſt parte of Aſia, lyeth a great countrye called Kathaie, or Kathaia: the boundes whereof extend themſelues on the North, and Eaſt, to the vttermoſt ſeas, and on the South to China. The people are not much learned, but more ciuill then the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> and haue good and ordinarie trafique with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries adioyning. This countrie hath in it many Kings, which are tributaries, and doe owe obedience vnto one, whome they call the great <hi>Cham</hi> or <hi>Cane</hi> of Kathaia: who is the chiefe gouernour of all the land: and eſteemed for multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, and largeneſſe of Dominion, to be one of the great Princes of the world: but his name is the leſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous: for that he lyeth ſo farre diſtant from the beſt nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and the paſſage vnto his countrie is ſo daungerous, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the perils of the ſeas, or for the long ſpace by land: his chiefe imperiall Citie is called <hi>Cambalu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the South-ſide of <hi>Kathaie,</hi> and Eaſt parte of Aſia next to the ſea, lyeth <hi>China.</hi> The people whereof, Oſorius deſcribeth by the name of <hi>Sine:</hi> and calleth their countrie <hi>Sinarunt regio.</hi> This is a fruitfull countrie and yeeldeth great ſtore of ritch commodities as almoſt any countrye in the
<pb facs="tcp:26616:11"/>worlde. It containeth in it very many ſeuerall kingdomes, which are abſolute Princes in their States. The chiefe cittie in this countrie is called <hi>Quinſay,</hi> and is deſcribed to be of incredible greatneſſe, Such a citie as were wont to bee in anntient time in the Eaſt: as Babylon, Nilus, and other. This countrie was firſt diſcouered by the late nauigation of the Portugals into the Eaſt Indies.</p>
               <p>The people of <hi>China</hi> are learned almoſt in all Artes, very skilfull workemen in curious fine workes of all ſortes: ſo that no countrie yeeldeth more precious marchandize then the workemanſhip of them.</p>
               <p>They are great ſouldiers, very politique and craftie, and in reſpecte thereof, contemning the wits of other vſing a Prouerbe, that all Nations doe ſee but with one eye: but that themſelues haue two.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Mathaeus</hi> hiſtoriographer to the King of Spaine for the Eaſterne Indies, doth reporte of them: that they haue had from very auntient time among them: theſe two things, which we holde to be the miracles of Chriſtendome, and but lately inuented. The one is the vſe of guns for their warres, &amp; the other is printing: which they vſe not as we do, writing from the left hand vnto the right: or as the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and <hi>Sirians;</hi> from the right hand vnto the left: but downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward directly: &amp; ſo their lines at the top to begin againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De India orientali.</head>
               <p>ON the South-ſide of China, toward the Molucco I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and the Indian ſea, lyeth the great countrie of India: extending it ſelfe from the South-eaſt part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, by the ſpace of many thouſand miles weſt-ward vnto the riuer Indus, which is the greateſt riuer in all that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, except Ganges, one of the greateſt riuers in the world, which lyeth in the Eaſt-part of the ſame Indies. This is that countrie, ſo famous in ancient time for the great riches ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for the multitude of people, for the conqueſt of Bacchus
<pb facs="tcp:26616:12"/>ouer it, for the paſſage thither of Alexander the great through all the length of Aſia: for his aduenturing to goe into the South Ocean with ſo mightie a Nauie, which fewe or none had euer attempted before him.</p>
               <p>This countrie had in auncient time, many abſolute king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and princes; as in the time of Alexander, Porus, Taxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and diuers others. In it were many Phyloſophers, and men of great learning: whome they called <hi>Gymneſophiſtae,</hi> of whome was Calanus, who burnt himſelfe afore Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The men of the South-parte of India are blacke, and therefore are called men of Inde. The cattle of all ſortes that are bred there, are of incredible bignes, in reſpect of other countries: as their Elephants, Apes, Munkies, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>The riches hereof hath bene very great with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of golde: inſomuch, that the Promontorie, which is now called Malach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, was in times paſt named <hi>Aurea Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneſus.</hi> The commoditie of ſpice is exceeding great that commeth from thence. The Portingales were the firſt, which by their long nauigations beyond the <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> and the farthermoſt parte of Africa, haue of late yeares diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered theſe countries of India. As heretofore of the King of Portingale: ſo now of the King of Spaine, who is repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted owner of them.</p>
               <p>The Portingales did finde diuers ſmall kingdomes at their firſt arriuall in thoſe partes, as the king of Calicut, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence commeth our Calicut linnen: the king of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baia, the king of Cananor, the king of Cochin, and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many other; with whome, they firſt entring league for trafique, and hauing leaue giuen to build Caſtles for their defence, they haue ſince by policie, encroched into their handes a great parte of the countrie which lyeth neare vnto the ſea-coaſt, and are mightie now, for the ſpace of many thouſand miles together. The king of Spaine hath there a vice-roy; whoſe reſidence, is commonly in the Imperiall citie called Goa. They doe euery yeare ſend home great
<pb facs="tcp:26616:12"/>ſtore of riche commodities into Spaine.</p>
               <p>The people of the countrie when the Portingales came firſt thither, were for the moſt part Gentiles: beleeuing no one God. But the Saracens, who reuerence the Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> from the baies, or gulfes of Perſia, and Arabia, did trafique much thither: ſo that <hi>Mahomet</hi> was known among them. But in one towne called Crangarior, they founde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Chriſtians, diffenting in many things from the Church of Rome, and rather agreeing with the Proteſtants: which Chriſtians had reteined by ſucceſſe their religion, from the time of Thomas the Apoſtle: by whom it is recorded by the auncient Eccleſiaſtical hiſtorie, part of India was conuerted</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Perſia.</head>
               <p>THere be diuers countries betweene <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Perſia:</hi> but they are not famous. <hi>Perſia</hi> is a large countrie, which lieth farre Weſt from <hi>India,</hi> it hath on the North <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyria, and Media:</hi> on the Weſt, <hi>Syria,</hi> and the <hi>Holyland:</hi> but next vnto it <hi>Meſopotamie:</hi> on the South, the maine Ocean, which entereth in notwithſtanding, by a bay called <hi>Sinus Perſicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that countrie, which in auncient time was ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed for the great riches and Empire thereof. Theſe were they, who took from the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> the Monarchies and did ſet vp in their countrie, the ſecond great Empire: which beganne vnder Cyrus: and continued vnto Darius: who was ouerthrowne by Alexander the great. In this Countrie raigned the great Kings: Cyrus, Canibiſes, Darius the ſonne of Hiſtaſpes, the great Xerxes, Artaxerxes, and many other: which in prophane writinges are famous for their warres againſt the <hi>Scythians, Aegyptians,</hi> and <hi>Graecians,</hi> and in the Scripture, for the deliuerie of the Iewes from Babylon by Cyrus; for building of the ſecond Temple at Ieruſalem: and for manie things which are mencioned of them in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of Daniel.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:13"/>
               <p>The people of this nation, although they were in former times very riotous, by reaſon of their great wealth: yet after that they loſt their Monarchy by the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> they haue growne great ſouldiers: and therefore as they euer did ſtrongly defend themſelues againſt the Romanes: ſo in the time of Conſtantine, and the other Emperours: they were fearfull neighbours to the Romane gouernment. And of late time, they haue ſtrongly oppoſed then ſelues agaynſt the Turkes, euer making their partie good with them. They fight commonlie on horſe-back &amp; are gouerned as in times paſt, by a King: ſo nowe, by an abſolute ruler and mightie Prince: whom they tearme the Shawe, or Sophie of Perſia. He hath many countries, and ſmall Kings in Aſſyria, and Media, and the countries adioyning tributaries.</p>
               <p>The Perſians are all at this day Sarazens in religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing on <hi>Mahomet:</hi> but as Papiſts and proteſtants do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for in opinion concerning the ſame Chriſt ſo do the Turkes and Perſians about their <hi>Mahomet:</hi> the one purſuing the other as heretikes with moſt deadly hatred. In ſo much, that there be in this reſpect almoſt continuall warres betweene the Turkes, and the Perſians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Parthia, &amp; Media.</head>
               <p>ON the North-eaſt, ſide of <hi>Perſia,</hi> lieth that countrie, which in old time was called <hi>Paerthia,</hi> but now named <hi>Arach,</hi> of whoſe great warres with the Medians, or Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, or Romanes, in Tacitus, and ancient hiſtories are true. The countrie boundeth on Media by the Weſt, which was in auncient time very full of people, whoſe fight as it is very much on horſ-backe, ſo the maner of them continually was for to giue an onſet, and then to runne their wayes: but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe like to the wilde Iriſh, ſo that no man was ſure when he had obtained any victorie ouer them.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the people that gaue the great ouerthrow to that rich <hi>Marcus Craſſus</hi> of Rome, who by reaſon his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:13"/>intending more to his getting of gold, then to the guiding of his armie, was ſlaine himſelfe, &amp; many thouſands of the Romanos. The Parthians with exprobration of his thirſt after mony, powring molten gold into his mouth after he was dead. Againſt theſe, the great Lucullus fought many battailes: but the Romanes were neuer able to bring them quite in ſubiection.</p>
               <p>On the Weſt-ſide of Parthia (the <hi>Mare Caſpium</hi> being on the North. Armenia on the Weſt, and Perſia on the South) Here lieth that country which in times paſt was called Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, but now Shiruan, or Seruan: which is at this day gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by many inferiour Kings and Princes which are tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, and do owe ſubiection to the Sophy of Perſia. So that he is the ſoueraigne Lord of all Media, as our Engliſh men haue founde: who paſſing through the dominion of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Ruſſia, haue croſſed the <hi>Mare Caſpium,</hi> and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſed with the inhabitants of this Media.</p>
               <p>This Nation in former time was verie famous: for the Medes were they that remoued the Empire from the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, vnto them: which as in themſelues it was nor great. So when by Cyrus it was loyned by the Perſians, it was verie mightie, and called by the name of the Empire of the Medes and Perſians. Here it was that Afryages reigned, the grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of Cyrus, and Darius of the Medes: the chiefe citie of this kingdome, was called Ecbatana, as the chiefe citie of Perſia, is Babylon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Armenia &amp; Aſſyria.</head>
               <p>ON the Weſt ſide of the <hi>Mare Caſpium,</hi> and of <hi>Media,</hi> lieth a countrie called by a generall name Armenia, which is by ſome diſtinctlie deuided into three partes: the North part whereof being but little, is called <hi>Georgia:</hi> the middle part <hi>Turcomania:</hi> and the thirde part, by the proper, name of Armenia: by which a man may ſee the reaſon of difference in diuers writers. Some ſaying that the countrie
<pb facs="tcp:26616:14"/>whence the Turkes firſt came, was Armenia: ſome ſay <hi>Turcomania:</hi> and ſome <hi>Georgia:</hi> the truth being, that out of one, or all theſe countries they be diſcended. Theſe Turkes are ſuppoſed to be the iſſue of them: whome Alexander the great did ſhut vp within certaine mountaines neare to the <hi>Mare Caſpium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is this one thing Memorable in Armenia: that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the great floud the Arke of Noah did reſt it ſelfe on the mountaines of Armenia: whereas Ioſephus witneſſeth, it is to be ſeene yet to this day. The hils wheron it reſted are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſome <hi>Noe montes.</hi> The people of this Nation haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained among them the Chriſtian faith, as it is thought, from the time of the Apoſtles: but at this day it is ſpotted with many abſurdities.</p>
               <p>On the South parte of Armenia bending towarde the Eaſt, lieth the countrie of Aſſyria, which is bounded on the Weſt with Meſopotamia. This country was that land, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the firſt Monarchie war ſetled, which began vnder <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> which the Scripture calleth <hi>Nimrod:</hi> liuing not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Noahs floud. And it ended in Sardanapalus: continuing for the ſpace of a thouſand and three hundred yeares. The King of this countrie was Senacharib; of whom we reade in the booke of Kings: and here raigned Nabuchadnezzer, who tooke Ieruſalem, and led the Iewes away priſoners vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Babylon.</p>
               <p>In this countrie, is the ſwift riuer Tygris, neare vnto the which, was Paradiſe: vpon this riuer ſtoode the great cittie Niniuie, called by prophane writers Ninus: which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of incredible bignes, and exceeding populous: but the nearneſſe of the riuer, and maruailous fruitfulnes of the ſoile, which Herodotus writeth: did returne their corne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times two, ſometimes three hundred folde, and did yeelde ſufficiencie for to maintaine it. This citie for a long time was the imperiall feat of the Monarchie: but being deſtroyed, as God foretolde it ſhould be by the Chaldeans: the reſidence
<pb facs="tcp:26616:14"/>of the king, was afterwards remoued vnto Babylon, a great citie in Chaldea, firſt built by Semiramis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Chaldaea.</head>
               <p>Next vnto Aſſyria, lieth Chaldaea: hauing on the Eaſt ſide Aſſyria, on the Weſt Syria, or Paleſtina: on the North Armenia: on the South the deſart of Arabia. This countrie is often called by the name of Meſopotamia, which name it hath, becauſe it lieth in the middle of two great riuers, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris, and Euphrates: it is called alſo by the name of <hi>Babilonia,</hi> which word of it ſelfe properly taken, doth ſignifie only that part of the countrie which ſtandeth about Babylon.</p>
               <p>The chiefe citie hereof was Babylon, the ruines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of doe remaine to this day. It was a rich and moſt pleaſant citie for all kind of delight: and was the imperiall citie of the Aſſyrians: where Nabuchadneſſar, and other their great kings did lie. It was to this citie, that the children of Iſrael were caried captiues: which thereof was called the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of Babylon. The kings of Perſia did alſo keepe their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence here: it was built vpon the riuer Euphrates, ſome part of it ſtandeth on the one ſide, and ſome on the other: hauing ſo the foundreſſe, Semiramis, the wife of Ninus.</p>
               <p>It is ſuppoſed by Diuines, that in this Meſopotamia, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the riuer Tygris &amp; Euphrates, Paradice did ſtand: this was the country wherin Abraham the Patriarke was borne: vnto the which the Romanes could very hardly extend their dominion. For they had much to do to get any ſuch gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any thing beyond the riuer Euphrates. From this people it is thought that the wiſe men came, which brought preſents vnto Chriſt, by the guiding of a ſtarre.</p>
               <p>For as in India and all the Eaſtern parts, ſo eſpecially in this countrie, their Noble men and Prieſtes, and verie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie people, doe giue themſelues to all Artes of diuination: Here were the great Southſayers, Enchaunters, and wiſe men, as they call them: here the firſt Aſtrologians, which
<pb facs="tcp:26616:15"/>are ſo deſcibed and derided in the Scripture: and agaynſt the inhabitants of Babylon and Chaldaea were the lawes of the Romanes made, againſt deuining Mathematicians: who in <hi>Tullie de Diuinatione, &amp; Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> as alſo in the lawes of the Emperours, are ordinary called by the name of Chaldeans: and in deede from theſe, and from the Egytians, is ſuppoſed to haue ſprung the firſt knowledge of Aſtronomie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Aſia minori,</head>
               <p>ON the North-weſt ſide of <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> lieth that countrie which is now called <hi>Nitolia:</hi> but in times paſt <hi>Aſia minor,</hi> hauing on the North-ſide <hi>Pontus Euxinus,</hi> on the Weſt, the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> and on the South, the maine <hi>Mare Mediterraneum.</hi> In the auncient writers, both of the Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and of the Romanes, this is oftentimes called by the ſingle name of <hi>Aſia,</hi> becauſe it was beſt knowne vnto them, and they were not ſo much acquainted with the farther places of <hi>Aſia</hi> the great.</p>
               <p>This countrie in generall, for the fruitfulneſſe of the land ſtanding in ſo temperate a Climate, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencie of the Sea euery way, and ſo many good hauens, hath beene reputed alwayes a verie commodious and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurefull countrie. It is wholie at this day vnder the Turke. The mountaine Taurus goeth along from the Weſt, vnto the Eaſt part of it.</p>
               <p>The greatneſſe of it is ſuch, that it hath comprehended many kingdomes and great prouinces, beſide cities of great fame. On the South-eaſt part thereof, neare Palaeſtina, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Cilicia: the chiefe citie thereof is Tarſus, the countrie of Saint Paul: the place whither Salomon ſent for great ſtore of his golde, and prouiſion for the Temple, whither Ionas alſo fled, when he ſhould haue gone to Niniue. In the ſtraites of this Cilicia, neere to the mountaine <hi>Taurus,</hi> did Alexander giue the great ouerthrowe in perſon to Darius,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:15"/>in the ioyning of their firſt battaile.</p>
               <p>Weſtward from <hi>Cilicia,</hi> lyeth the prouince called <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia:</hi> wherein ſtandeth the citie <hi>Saeleucia,</hi> built by Seleucus, one of the foure great ſucceſſors of Alexander the great.</p>
               <p>On the Weſt of this <hi>Pamphilia,</hi> extending it ſelfe euen to the ſea, is <hi>Lydia,</hi> where reigned ſometime Croeſus, who was ſo renowmed for his aboundant riches. Herein ſtandeth as a ſea-towne, <hi>Halicarnaſſus</hi> the countrie of Herodotus, and of Dionyſius, who wrote the Romane Hiſtorie: which cittie was ſometimes a kingdome, as in the time of Xerxes: to whoſe aide againſt the Graecians, did goe Artimiſia, the Queene of Halicarnaſſe, and here raigned Ada another Queene, in the time of Alexander the great.</p>
               <p>Vpon the ſea-coaſt, Northward from <hi>Lydia,</hi> ſtandeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thoſe cities, vnto the which, <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Reuellation did write his ſeuen Epiſtles, as <hi>Smyrna, Pergamus, Sardis,</hi> and <hi>Epheſus:</hi> but other of them, as <hi>Laodicia, Philadelphia, Thia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tira,</hi> doe ſtand more in the inland.</p>
               <p>Sardis was a citie of great pleaſure and profite: which is that place, the winning whereof by the Greekes did ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe one of the kings of Perſia; that he cauſed it euerie day at dinner to be remembred vnto him, that the Graecians had taken Sardis: and that he muſt not ceaſe till he had recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epheſus</hi> was one of the moſt famous cities of the worlde, the greateſt glorie whereof did ariſe by reaſon of the moſt magnificent Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> which was at <hi>Epheſus:</hi> to the building whereof all Aſia the leſſe did verie bountifully contribute.</p>
               <p>It is reported to haue beene two hundred yeeres in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and at ſeuen ſeuerall times, as otherwiſe, ſo eſpeciallie by lightning, to haue bin ſet on fire: but the final deſtruction of it was by a baſe perſon named Heroſtratus: who of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſet it on fire, to make himſelfe famous.</p>
               <p>More Northward toward the Sea-coaſt lyeth <hi>Phrygia,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26616:16"/>which was the countrie from whence the Goddeſſe called <hi>Bona Dea,</hi> or <hi>Peſſinuntia,</hi> and <hi>Cybile</hi> was brought to Rome. In this countrie liued Gordius, who knit that knot that Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander cut: hoping thereby to obtaine (as an oracle had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde) the whole kingdome of Aſia. In this countrie ſtoode Troy, the ſiege whereof by the Graecians, is made ſo famous by the Poetrie of Homer and of Virgil.</p>
               <p>Yet Northwarde from Phrygia lyeth the Countrie of Bithynia, which was ſometimes a kingdome where Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias raigned, that had ſo much to doe with the Romanes. In this countrie ſtandeth the citie <hi>Nicea,</hi> where the firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councel was held againſt Arrius the Heretike, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine the great: thereof called the <hi>Nicene Councell.</hi> Here ſtandeth alſo <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> where the fourth general Councell was held by the Emperour Martianus, againſt the heretike Neſtorius.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Bithynia</hi> Eaſt-ward, on the North-ſide of Aſia the leſſe, ſtandeth the countrie of <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> where was the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie built by Pompey the great, called of his name <hi>Pompeio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis.</hi> From thence Eaſtward, ioining to Armenia, is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Capadocia,</hi> which bordereth on Armenia: &amp; North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from thence, near to the ſea called <hi>Pontus Euxinus,</hi> lieth the kingdome of Mithridates: which was called <hi>Pontus.</hi> This Mithridates had long warres with the Romanes, whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects he cauſed to be ſlaine all in one night throughout Aſia the leſſe. He was afterward ouerthrowne by Pempey the great Romane. By him was inuented that preſeruatiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poiſon, which of his name is called Mithridate. There were alſo in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe ſome other ſmall countries, as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia, Lycia, Caria,</hi> and ſome other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Syria, &amp; Palaeſtina.</head>
               <p>SOuthward from <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, lieth <hi>Syria,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Palaeſtina,</hi> hauing on the Eaſt <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> on the South <hi>Arabia,</hi> on the Weſt <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> and the end of the
<pb facs="tcp:26616:16"/>
                  <hi>Mediterran ſea.</hi> The people of this <hi>Syria,</hi> were in times paſt called the <hi>Aramites.</hi> In their language is the tranſlation of the new Teſtament, called the <hi>Syriacke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this countrie ſtandeth <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was ſometimes one of the famous Patriarks ſeas, and is a citie of reckoning vnto this day. Here alſo ſtandeth now the Citie of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> which is a famous Mart towne for the Marchandizing of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and other of the Eaſt, and for the Turkes, and ſuch countries as bee adioyning. Here ſtandeth alſo <hi>Tripolis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The South part of <hi>Syria,</hi> lying downe toward <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> was the place where the children of Iſrael did dwel; beeing a countrie but of ſmall quantitie, not in length two hundren Italian miles: yet was ſo fruitfull, flowing with milk and honie (as the ſcripture calleth it) that both it did main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aboue thirtie kings and their people, before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the children of Iſrael out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and alſo was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient afterwarde to relieue the incredible number of the twelue tribes of Iſrael.</p>
               <p>It was noted of this countrie, that whereas by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Climate wherein it ſtoode, and the fertilitie of the ſoile (but eſpecially by the bleſſing of God) it was the moſt fruitfull land that was in the world: nowe our trauailers by experience doe finde the countrie, in reſpect of the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, to bee changed; God curſing the land, together with the Iewes, the inhabitants of it. It is obſerued alſo for all the Eaſterne parts, that they are not ſo fertile as they haue beene in former ages. The earth as it were growing olde, which is an argument of the diſſolution to come by the day of iudgement.</p>
               <p>Through this countrie doth runne the riuer <hi>Iordan,</hi> which hath heretofore beene famous for the fruitfulneſſe of the trees ſtanding thereupon, and for the mildneſſe of the aire, ſo that (as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> writeth) when ſnow hath layen in other places of the land, about the riuer it hath bin ſo calme
<pb facs="tcp:26616:17"/>that men did goe in ſingle thinne linnen garments.</p>
               <p>In this countrie ſtandeth the Lake called <hi>Lacus Aſphalti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> becauſe of a kinde of ſlime, or <hi>Bytumen,</hi> which dayly it doth caſt vp, being of force to ioyne ſtones exceeding faſt in building.</p>
               <p>This Lake is it, which is called <hi>Mare mortuum,</hi> a Sea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſalt and dead, for that no liuing thing is therein: the water whereof is ſo thicke, that fewe thinges will ſinke therein: inſomuch, that <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſaith, that an Oxe hauing all his legges bound, will not ſinke in that water.</p>
               <p>The nature of this lake was turned into this qualitie, when God did deſtroy <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorra,</hi> and the citties adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with fire and brimſtone from heauen: for <hi>Sodom</hi> and the other cities did ſtand neare vnto <hi>Iordan,</hi> and to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re mortuum:</hi> for the deſtruction of whome, all that coaſt to this day is a witnes: the earth ſmelling of brimſtone, being deſolate, and yeelding no fruite ſauing apples, and ſuch, which growing with a faire ſhewe to the eye lyke other fruite: aſſone as they are touched, turne preſently to aſhes: as beſides <hi>Ioſephus, Solinus</hi> doth witnes.</p>
               <p>The land of <hi>Palaeſtina</hi> had for inhabitants all the twelue tribes of Iſraell, which were vnder one kingdome, till the time of Rehoboam the ſonne of Salomon. But then were they deuided into two kingdomes: ten tribes being called <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and two being called <hi>Iuda,</hi> whoſe chiefe Citie was called <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Then the tribes after much Idolatrie, were caried priſoners into <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and the kingdome diſſolued: other people being placed in their roome in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the countrie adioyning.</p>
               <p>The other two tribes were properly called the Iewes, &amp; their land <hi>Iudaea,</hi> which continued long after in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and thereabout, till the captiuitie of <hi>Babylon:</hi> where they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for 70. yeares. They were afterward reſtored: but liued without glory till the comming of Chriſt. But ſince his time, for a curſe vpon them and their children, for putting Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:26616:17"/>to death, they are ſcattered vpon the face of the earth as run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagates, without certaine countrie, King, Prieſt, or Prophet.</p>
               <p>In their chiefe Citie <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was the Temple of God, firſt moſt gloriouſly built by Salomon, and afterwarde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by Nabuchadnezzer. By the commaundement of Cyrus King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> was a ſecond Temple built, much more baſe then the former: for beſides the pouertie, and ſmalneſſe of it, there wanted fiue thinges which were in the former, as the Iewes write. Firſt the Arke of the couenant: Secondly, the pot of Manna: Thirdly, the rod of Aron: Fourthly, the two tables of the lawe written by the finger of God: and fiftly, the fire for the ſacrifice which came downe from heauen. Herod the great, an Edomite ſtranger, hauing gotten the kingdome, contrary to the lawe of Moſes, and knowing the people to be offended therewithall, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their fauour, did build a third Temple, much more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then the ſecond, which was that Temple wherein our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles did teach.</p>
               <p>The Citie of Ieruſalem was twiſe taken, and vtterly laid deſolate: firſt by Nabuchadnezzer at the captiuitie of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> and ſecondly after the death of Chriſt by Veſpatian the Romaine (who firſt began the ſiege) and by his ſonne Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, who was afterward Emperour of <hi>Rome:</hi> who brought ſuch horrible deſolation on that Citie, and the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by ſire, ſworde, and famine, that the lyke hath not bin read in any hiſtorie. He did afterward put thouſands of them on ſome one day, to be deuoured by the beaſtes, which was a cruell cuſtome of the Romaine magnificence.</p>
               <p>After this deſtruction, the land of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> and the ruines of Ieruſalem, were poſſeſſed by ſome of the people adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till that aboute 600. yeares ſince, the Sarazens did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade it: for the expelling of whome from thence, diuers Frenchmen, and other Chriſtians, vnder the leading of Godfrey of Bullen, did aſſemble themſelues: thinking it a great ſhame, that the Holy land as they called it, the Citie
<pb facs="tcp:26616:18"/>of Ieruſalem, and the place of the ſepulchre of Chriſt, ſhould be in the hands of the Infidels.</p>
               <p>This Godfrey ruled in Ieruſalem by the name of a Duke: but his ſucceſſors after him, for the ſpace of ſixe ſcore yeares, called themſelues Kings of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> aboute which time, Saladine who called himſelfe King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, did win it from the Ch iſtians: for the recouery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Richard the firſt, King of England, together with the French King, and the King of <hi>Cicilia,</hi> did goe in perſon with their armies to Ieruſalem: but although they wonne many thinges from the infidels, yet the ende was, that the Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens did retaine the Holy land.</p>
               <p>The whole countrie and citie of Ieruſalem, are now in the dominion of the Turke: who notwithſtanding for a great tribute, doeth ſuffer many Chriſtians to abide there. There are therefore nowe two, or more monaſteries, and religious houſes where Friers doe abide, and make a good commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie by ſhewing of the ſepulchre of Chriſt, and other monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vnto ſuch Chriſtian pilgrims, as doe vſe ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to goe in pilgrimage to the Holy land. The King of Spaine calleth himſelfe at this day, King of Ieruſalem.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Arabia.</head>
               <p>NExt vnto the Holy land, lyeth the great countrie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia,</hi> hauing on the North-parte <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> and <hi>Meſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia:</hi> on the Eaſt the gulfe of <hi>Perſia:</hi> on the South the maine Ocean of <hi>India</hi> or <hi>Aethiopia:</hi> on the Weſt, <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and the great bay called <hi>Sinus Arabicus,</hi> or the redde ſea. This countrie is deuided into three partes: the North parte whereof, is called <hi>Arabia deſerta;</hi> the South parte, which is the greateſt, is named <hi>Arabia Foelix,</hi> and in the middle betweene both, which for the aboundance of Rockes and Stones, is called <hi>Arabia Petrea,</hi> or <hi>Petroſa.</hi> The deſerte of <hi>Arabia</hi> is that place, in which God after the deliuery of the Iſraelites from Egypt, by paſſing through the red ſea, did
<pb facs="tcp:26616:18"/>keepe his people vnder Moſes for fortie yeares, becauſe of their rebellion; feeding them in the meane time with <hi>Manna</hi> from heauen, &amp; ſometime with water miraculouſly drawne out of drie rockes: for the country hath verie little water, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no trees, and is vtterly vnfit for tillage or corne. There are no townes nor inhabitants in all this deſert: in <hi>Arabia Petroſa</hi> are ſome, but not many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arabia Foelix,</hi> for fruitfulnes of the ground, and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtanding euerie way towarde the ſea, is one of the beſt countries of the world: but the principall cauſe why it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Foelix,</hi> is for that it yeeldeth many things in aboundance, which in other parts of the world are not to be had: as Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, eſpecially the moſt precious balmes, myrhe, and many other, both fruits and ſpices, and it yeeldeth withall, ſtore of ſome precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>This is that countrie wherein <hi>Mahomet</hi> wes borne, who being of meane parentage, was brought vp in his youth in the trade of merchandiſe; but afterward ioyning himſelfe with theeues and robbers, his life was to rob ſuch marchants as paſſed through <hi>Arabia;</hi> and to this purpoſe hauing gotten togither many of his owne countrimen, he had afterwardes a whole legion or more out of the Romane ſouldiours: who being offended with <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Romane Emperour, for want of their pay, ioined themſelues to him: ſo that at length hee had a great armie, wherewith hee ſpoyled the countrie adioyning.</p>
               <p>To maintaine his credit &amp; authoritie with his owne men, he fained that he had conference with the holy Ghoſt, at ſuch time as he was troubled with the falling ſicknes, and accordingly, he ordained a new religion, conſiſting partly of Iewiſh ceremonies, and partly of Chriſtian doctrine, and ſome other things of his owne inuention, that hee might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueagle both Iewes and Chriſtians, and yet by his own fancy diſtinguiſh his followers from both. The booke of his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is called the Alcoran. The people which were his Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries
<pb facs="tcp:26616:19"/>(whereas in deed they came of Hagar the hand maid of Sara Abrahams wife: and therefore ſhould of her be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iſmaelites, or Hagarens) becauſe they would not ſeeme to be come of a bond woman, and from him whom they ſuppoſe a baſtard: they terme themſelues Sarazens, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from Sara, they are called by ſome writers Arabians in ſtead of Sarazens, their name beeing drawne from their firſt countrie.</p>
               <p>In the countrie of <hi>Arabia</hi> ſtandeth a citie called <hi>Mecha,</hi> which is the place where Mahomet was buried, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of him there is built a great Temple: vnto the which, the Turkes and Sarazens doe yearlie goe on pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, as ſome Chriſtians do to the Holie land. For they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Mahomet to be the greateſt Prophet that euer came into the world: ſaying that there were three great Prophets Moſes, Chriſt, and Mahomet: and as the doctrine of Moſes was bettered by Chriſt, ſo is the doctrine of Chriſt amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Mahomet. In this reſpect, as we reckon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of our yeares from the incarnation of Chriſt, ſo the Sarazens account theirs from the time of Mahomet. The Turkes, whoſe fame began now about two hundred yeares ſince, haue imbraced the opinions and the religion of the Sarazens, concerning Mahomet.</p>
               <p>On the Weſt-ſide of <hi>Arabia,</hi> betweene that, and Egypt, lieth the gulfe called of the country, <hi>Sinus Arabicus,</hi> by ſome <hi>Mare Erythreum,</hi> but commonly the red Sea: not of one <hi>Erythrus</hi> as ſome ſuppoſe; but becauſe the ſand and bankes there-about are in colour red. This is that ſea, through the which, by Moſes, the people of Iſrael were led, when they fled out of Egypt from Pharao: God cauſing by his power, the waters to ſtand on both ſides of them, which they paſſed through as on drie land.</p>
               <p>This is that ſea, through the which, the ſpices of the Eaſt Indies were in times paſt brought to <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt.</hi> and from thence diſperſed into Chriſtendome by the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians:
<pb facs="tcp:26616:19"/>which ſpices and Apothicarie drugs are found to be far worſe then before time they were, by reaſon of the great moiſture which they take on the water, by the long nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Portingales, by the backe part of <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that ſea, through the which Salomon did ſend for his golde, and other precious marchandiſe vnto the Eaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and not to the Weſt Indies, as ſome lately haue diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Whereout the vanitie of that opinion may appeare, that America and the Weſt Indies were knowne in the time of Salomon: for if he had ſent thither, his courſe had beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the <hi>Med.</hi> and through the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Fretum Herculeum,</hi> between Spaine and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie. But the Scripture telleth, that the nauie which Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſent forth, was built at <hi>Eſeon Gabar:</hi> which there alſo is ſaid to ſtand on the red ſea: ſo his courſe might be Eaſt-ward or South-ward, not Weſt-ward.</p>
               <p>In the deſert of <hi>Arabia</hi> is the Mount <hi>Horeb:</hi> which by ſome is ſuppoſed to bee the ſame that is called the Mount Sina: where manie thinke it was, that Abraham ſhoulde haue offered vp his ſonne Iſaac: but it is certaine, that it was the place, where God in the Wilderneſſe, did giue vnto the people of Iſrael his law of the ten commaundements, with thundering, lightning, and earth-quake, in moſt fearefull manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Africa, &amp; Egypto.</head>
               <p>FRom <hi>Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Palaſtina,</hi> toward the Weſt, lyeth <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica;</hi> hauing on the North-ſide, from the one end of it to the other, the <hi>Mediter. ſea.</hi> The greateſt part of which countrie, although it hath beene geſſed at by writers in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, yet becauſe of the great heate of it, lying for the moſt parte vnder the <hi>Zona Torrida,</hi> and for the Wilderneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therein, it was in former times ſuppoſed by manie, not to bee much inhabited: but of certaintie by all, verie little diſcouered: till the Portingales of late beganne their naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb facs="tcp:26616:20"/>on the backe-ſide of <hi>Africa,</hi> to the Eaſt Indies. So ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act a deſcription is not therefore to bee looked for, as hath beene of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Eurupa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ioyned to the Holy land by a little Iſthmos is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which is a land moſt fruitfull, as any almoſt in the world, although in theſe daies it doth not anſwere to the felicitie of former time. This is it which in the time of Ioſeph did relieue Canaan with corne, and the familie of Iacob, which did ſo multiplie in the land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> that they were growne to an huge multitude, when God by Moſes did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them from thence. This countrie did yeeld exceeding aboundance of corne vnto the citie of Rome, whereupon <hi>Aegypt,</hi> as well as <hi>Cicilia,</hi> was commonly called <hi>Horreum populi Romani.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is obſerued from all antiquitie, that almoſt neuer any raine did fall in the land of Egypt: whereupon the raining, with thunder, &amp; lightning, and fire running on the ground, was ſo much the more ſtrange: when God plagued Pharao in the dayes of Moſes. But the flowing of the riuer Nilus ouer all the countrie (their cities onely and ſome fewe hils excepted) doth ſo water the earth, that it bringeth foorth fruit abundantly. The flowing of which riuer yearly is one of the greateſt miracles of the world, no man being able to yeeld a ſufficient and aſſured reaſon thereof: although in Herodotus, and Diodorus Siculus, many probable cauſes and opinions are aſſigned thereof.</p>
               <p>It is noted of this riuer, if in ordinarie places it doe flow vnder the height of fifteene cubites, that for want of moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, the yeare is not fruitfull; and if it do flow aboue ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene cubites, that there is like to bee a dearth by reaſon of the aboundance of the moyſture, the water lying longer on the land then the inhabitants do deſire.</p>
               <p>In Egypt hath learning bin very auncient. But eſpecially the knowledge of Aſtronomie and Mathematicks: whereof before the time of Tullie, their Prieſts would report, that
<pb facs="tcp:26616:20"/>they had the diſcent for 1500. yeares exactly recorded, with obſeruation Aſtrologicall: which as it is a fable, vnleſſe they doe reckon their yeares by the Moone (as ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they did euery moneth, for a yeare) ſo it doth argue knowledge to haue bene among them very antient: their Prieſtes had among them a kinde of writing, and of deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing thinges by picture: which they did call their <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This in times paſt was a kingdome, and by the Kinges thereof were built thoſe great <hi>Pyramides,</hi> which were held to be one of the ſeuen wonders of the world, being mightie huge buildings, erected of exceeding height, for the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of their founders. There is part of two or three of them remaining vnto this day. In <hi>Aegipt</hi> did ſtand the great Citie <hi>Memphis,</hi> which is at this day called <hi>Cairo,</hi> one of the moſt famous Cities of the Eaſt. Here did Alexander build that Citie, which vnto this day is of his name called Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, bing now the greateſt Citie of merchandize in all <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt:</hi> of which <hi>Ammiamus Marcellinus</hi> doth obſerue, that there is neuer any day, or almoſt hath euer bene: but that once in that day, the Sun hath bene ſeene to ſhine ouer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria.</hi> This Citie was one of the foure principall ſeas, and remaineth ſo at this time.</p>
               <p>This countrie was gouerned by a King, as long agone, as almoſt any in the worlde. Here raigned Amaſis, who made thoſe good lawes ſpoken of by Herodotus, and Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus, in whoſe writings the antient cuſtomes of the <hi>Aegiptians</hi> are worthie to be read.</p>
               <p>After Alexanders time, Ptolomeus one of his captaines had this kingdome, of whome all his ſucceſſors were called Ptolomeis, as before time all their Kings were called Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao. They continued long friendes, and in league with the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> till the time of Iulius Caeſar: but afterward they were as ſubiects to the Romaines, till the Empire did decaye,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:21"/>
               <p>When they had withdrawne themſelues from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine gouernement, they ſet vp a Prince of their owne: whome they tearmed the Sultan, or Souldan of <hi>Aegipt:</hi> of whome, about 400. yeares ſinee, Saladine was one. But when the race of theſe was out, the Mamalukes (who were the garde of the Sultan, as the Ianiſaries to the Turke) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Prince at their pleaſure, till that nowe aboute an 100. yeares agone, or leſſe, the Turke poſſeſſed himſelfe with ſole gouernement of the countrie: ſo that at this day, <hi>Aegipt</hi> is wholy vnder the Turke.</p>
               <p>There be Chriſtians that now liue in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> for their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto the Turke, as they doe now in <hi>Graecia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Cyrene &amp; Africa minori.</head>
               <p>ON the Weſt-ſide of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> lying along the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> is a countrie which is called in olde time <hi>Cyrene:</hi> wherein did ſtand that Oracle which was ſo famous in the time of Alexander the great, called by the name of the Temple or Oracle of <hi>Iupiter Hammon:</hi> whither, when Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander did repaire, as to aske counſell of himſelfe and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, the Prieſts being before taught what they ſhould ſay, did flatteringly profeſſe him to be the ſonne of a God, and that he was to be adored: ſo that as the Oracle of <hi>Delphos,</hi> and ſome other were plaine deluſions of Satan, who did raigne in that darke time of ignorance, ſo this of <hi>Iupiter Hammon</hi> may be well ſuppoſed to bee nothing elſe but a couſinage of the Prieſtes.</p>
               <p>In this countrie and all neare aboute where the Oracle ſtoode, are very great wilderneſſes: where did appeare to Alexander, for foure dayes iourney, neither Graſſe, Tree, Water, Man, Bird, nor Beaſt; but onely a deep kinde of ſand: ſo that he was inforced to carry water with him for himſelfe and his company, and all other prouiſion on Camels backs. At this day this countrie hath loſt his olde name, and is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned as a parte of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and lyeth vnder the Turke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:21"/>
               <p>Weſtward from hence, along the <hi>Mediterran,</hi> lyeth the countrie which in auntient time was called <hi>Afried minor:</hi> for as in <hi>Aſia</hi> one part aboue another was by an excellencie called <hi>Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe: ſo this parte of <hi>Afrike</hi> was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Romaines ſometimes <hi>Africa</hi> ſimply, ſometimes <hi>Afica</hi> the leſſe. In this countrie did ſtand that place ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, mentioned by Saluſt: vnder the neme of <hi>Phileni Arae,</hi> which was the bound in that time, betweene <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Cyrene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the Notth and Eaſt parte hereof, in the ſea neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſhore, was that quicke-ſand, which in times paſt did deſtroy ſo many ſhippes: and was called <hi>Syrtis Magna:</hi> as alſo, on the North and Weſt parte was the other ſand, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Syrtis parua.</hi> Some part of this countrie was heretofore vnder the Sultane of Egypt, whoſe dominion did extend it ſelfe ſo far to the Weſt: &amp; there it was deuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Tunis:</hi> but it is now wholy vnder the Turke, and is commonly reputed as a parte of <hi>Barbarie.</hi> For now by the generall name, from the confines of <hi>Cyrene</hi> vnto the Weſt, as farre as Hercules his pillars, all the whole ſpace is called <hi>Barbarie:</hi> though it conteine in it diuers kingdomes, as Tunis, Feſſa, and Marocco.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Mauritania Caeſarienſi.</head>
               <p>AParte of that countrie, which by a generall name is called at this day <hi>Barbary,</hi> hath in olde time bin cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mauritania,</hi> which was deuided into two partes: the Eaſt part whereof next to <hi>Africa minor,</hi> was called by the Romaines <hi>Mauritania Caeſarienſis,</hi> as the other was called <hi>Mauritania Tingitana.</hi> In <hi>Mauritania Caeſarienſis</hi> was the countrie of <hi>Numidia,</hi> the people whereof were vſed in the warres of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> as light-horſe men, and for nimble ſeruices very actiue.</p>
               <p>In the Eaſt-parte of this countrie ſtanding in the Sea, was that amous Citie of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſuppoſed to be built by
<pb facs="tcp:26616:22"/>
                  <hi>Dido,</hi> who came from <hi>Tyrus.</hi> This Citie was it which for the ſpace of ſome hundreth yeares contended with <hi>Rome</hi> for the Empire of the worlde. In the Romaine hiſtories are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded three great warres which the people of <hi>Rome</hi> had with the Citie of <hi>Carthage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt of the three, their contention was for the Iles of <hi>Cicilia, Corſica,</hi> and <hi>Sardinia:</hi> when the victorie fell to the Romaines, and the Carthaginians were glad to redeeme their peace with the leauing of thoſe Ilands. The ſecond warre was begunne by Hannibal, who brake the league, and after he had taken ſome parte of Spaine from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and ſacked <hi>Saguntum,</hi> a citie of their friendes, came firſt ouer the Pyrenie hills to <hi>France,</hi> then ouer the Alpes to <hi>Italie,</hi> where he ouerthrew the Romaines in three great bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes: and much endaungered their ſtate: he continued in <hi>Italie</hi> with his armie ſixteene yeares: till Scipio attempting on <hi>Carthage,</hi> forced Hannibal to returne to reſcue his owne countrie. There was Hannibal ouerthrowne, and his Citie put to a great penſion by Scipio: who for his victorie there, was named Africanus.</p>
               <p>In the third warre, becauſe the people of <hi>Cartharge</hi> ſtill brake their leage, their Citie was razed to the very grounde, by the earneſt and continuall ſure of Cato the elder, fearing euermore ſo dangerous a neighbour, though Scipio Naſica counſelled to the contrarie: fearing leaſt if the dread of that enemie were taken away, the Romanes would grow eyther to idlenes, or to ciuill diſſenſion, which after they did. It is reported of Cato, that he neuer ſpake his iudgement of any thing in the Senate, but his concluſion was thus: Thus I thinke for this matter, and withall, that <hi>Carthage</hi> is to be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed downe. And Scipio Naſica would reply in his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Thus I thinke of this matter, and withall, that <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> is not to be razed downe.</p>
               <p>In this countrie towards the Weſt not far from <hi>Carthage</hi> ſtood <hi>Vtica,</hi> whereof the younger Cato was termed <hi>Cato Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26616:22"/>becauſe hee killed himſelfe there, in the ciuill warres betweene Pompey and Caeſar: becauſe he would not come within the handes of his enemie Caeſar. Not farre from thence Weſtwarde ſtandeth <hi>Hippon,</hi> which was the Citie where S. Auſten was Biſhop. This whole countrie at this day is called the kingdome of <hi>Tunis,</hi> the king whereof is a kinde of Stipendarie vnto the great Turke. The people that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit there are generally Sarazens, and do profeſſe Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Mauritania Tingitana.</head>
               <p>THe other part of Barbarie that lieth along the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</hi> fartheſt into the weſt was called in olde time <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritania Tingitana.</hi> The people of which countrie were thoſe which almoſt in all olde hyſtories were called by the name of <hi>Mauri.</hi> Thoſe of the other <hi>Mauritania</hi> being rather ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Namidae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into the Northweſt part hereof did Hercules come, and there did ſet vp one of his pillars, which aunſwereth to the other in Spaine, at the ſtraights of <hi>Gibraltar</hi> in times paſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Fretum Herculeum.</hi> On the South part hereof lay the kingdome of Bocchus, which in the time of Marius had ſo much to doe with the Romanes. In the Weſtpart of this <hi>Mauritania,</hi> ſtandeth the hill called <hi>Atlas minor;</hi> and on the South part is the great hill called <hi>Atlas maior,</hi> whereof the maine Ocean which lieth betweene <hi>Mauritania</hi> and <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> is called <hi>Mare Atlanticum.</hi> This hill is ſo high, that vnto thoſe who ſtoode on the bottome of it, it ſeemed to touch heauen with his top: whereupon grew that fable of the Poets, that Atlas was a giant, who helde vp heauen with his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>This countrie hath beene long inhabited by the Sarazens, who from thence, finding it to be but a ſhort paſſage into <hi>Spain,</hi> did go ouer now ſeuen hundred yeers agone: and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed there the kingdome of <hi>Granado</hi> on the South-ſide of
<pb facs="tcp:26616:23"/>
                  <hi>Spaine:</hi> till they were thence expelled by Ferdinandus and Elizabeth, or Iſabell, King and Queene of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this countrie ſince that time, haue the Spaniards taken ſome cities and holdes: and ſo alſo haue the Portingales: which by the diuers euent of victorie, haue often beene loſt and wonne by them.</p>
               <p>Here it was that the Emperou: Charles the fift had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of his great warres agaynſt the Moores, as well as in the kingdome of <hi>Timis.</hi> For the aſſiſtance of one, who claimed to bee King of a part of this Countrie, did Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian the king of <hi>Portingale</hi> goe with all his power into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> in the yeare 1578. where vnaduiſedly bearing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee was ſlaine togither with two other, dying that day, who claymed to bee Kings: ſo that there it was, that the battaile was ſought: whereof it is ſaid, that three kings dyed in one day: which battaile was the ruine of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Portingale:</hi> and the cauſe of the vniting of a to the Crowne of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Aſtrolegers did ſuppoſe, that the blaging Starre which appeared the yeare before did ſignifie that ill euent.</p>
               <p>This whole countrie doth containe in it, beſides, ſome imperiall gouernment, two abſolute kingdomes: the one the kingdome of <hi>Eezza,</hi> or <hi>Fes,</hi> which lieth on the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part toward the <hi>Mediter.</hi> and <hi>Spaine:</hi> the other is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Marocco,</hi> which lieth from about the hill <hi>Atlas mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> to the South and Weſt part of <hi>Mauritania.</hi> Theſe are both Sarazens, as be alſo their people: holding true league with the Turke; and with ſome other Chriſtian Princes, a league onely for trefique or Marchandiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De reliquis Africae regionbius. maritimis.</head>
               <p>FRom beyond the hils <hi>Atlas maior,</hi> vnto the South of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica</hi> is nothing almoſt in antiquitie worthy the reading,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:23"/>and thoſe things which are written for the moſt part are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. In the new Writers there are ſome few things to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferued As firſt, that all the people in generall to the South, lying within the <hi>Zona torrida,</hi> are not onely blackiſh like the Moores; but are exceedingly blacke. And therefore as in olde time, by an excellencie, ſome of them were called <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grita;</hi> ſo that to this day they are named Negros, as then whome no men are blacker.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the inhabitants of all theſe parts which bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or the ſea coaſt, euen vnto <hi>Caput bonae ſpei,</hi> haue beene Gentiles, adoring Images and fooliſh ſhapes for their gods; neither hearing of Chriſt, nor beleeuing on Mahomet, till ſuch time as Portingales co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in among them, haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt for themſelues; but haue wonne fewe of the people to imbrace their religion. Thirdly, that the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales paſſing along <hi>Africa</hi> vnto the Eaſt Indies, haue fetled themſelues in many places of thoſe countries, building Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and townes for their owne ſafetie, and to keepe the people in ſubiection to their great commoditie.</p>
               <p>One of the firſt countries famous beyond <hi>Marocco,</hi> is <hi>Guinea,</hi> which we call <hi>Ginnie:</hi> within the compaſſe whereof lieth the cape called <hi>Cape <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erde:</hi> and the other, the <hi>Cape</hi> of the three points, and the towne and Caſtle named <hi>Sierra Liona,</hi> at which places commonly all trauailers doe touch that doe paſſe that way for freſh water, and other ſhippe-prouiſion. Our Engliſh men haue founde trafique into the partes of this countrie: where their greateſt commoditie as golde, and Elephants teeth: of both which there is very good ſtore.</p>
               <p>Beyond that toward the South, not farre from the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall line, lyeth the kingdome of <hi>Congo,</hi> commonlie called <hi>Manicongo:</hi> Where the Portingales at their firſt arriuall, finding the people to bee heathens without God, did induce them to a profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt: and to bee baptized in great aboundance: allowing of the principles
<pb facs="tcp:26616:24"/>of religion: vntill ſuch time as the Prieſts did teach them to leade their liues according vnto their profeſſion: which the moſt part of them in no caſe enduring, they returned backe againe vnto their Gentiliſme.</p>
               <p>Beyond <hi>Manicongo,</hi> ſo farre to the South as almoſt ten degrees beyonde the tropicke of Capricorne, lyeth the landes ende: which is a promontorie, now called by the name of <hi>Caput bone ſpei:</hi> which Vaſcus Gama the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale did diſcouer, and ſo called it: becauſe hee had there good hope that the land did turne to the North: and that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the courſe thereof, he might bee brought to <hi>Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Perſia:</hi> but eſpecially to <hi>Calicut</hi> in <hi>India.</hi> Which courſe, when himſelfe and other of his countrimen after him did follow: they founde on the coaſt vp towarde <hi>Arabia,</hi> the kingdome of <hi>Mozambique, Melinde, Magadaxa,</hi> and other: whoſe people were all Gentiles, and now are in league with the Portingales: who haue built diuerſe holdes for their ſafetie: of which Countries and manners of the people, he that liſteth to reade, may finde much in the hyſtories of Oſorius, and Petrus Maffeus. But there is no matter of any great importance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Abiſsina, &amp; imperio Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri Iohannis.</head>
               <p>IN the inland of <hi>Africa</hi> lyeth a verie large Countrie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it ſelfe on the Eaſt, to ſome part of the redde ſea; on the South, to the kingdome of <hi>Melinde,</hi> and a great way farther; on the North, vnto <hi>Egypt;</hi> on the Weſt vnto <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corgo:</hi> the people whereof are called <hi>Abiſſini,</hi> and it ſelfe, the dominion of him, whom wee commonly call in Engliſh Preſter Iohn: but in Latine ſome tearme him, <hi>Precioſus Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes,</hi> becauſe of his riches; but in the moſt part <hi>Presbiter Iohannes:</hi> writing of him, that as he is a prince abſolute, ſo he hath alſo a Prieſtlike, or Patriarchall function &amp; iuriſdiction
<pb facs="tcp:26616:24"/>among them. This is a very mightie prince, and reputed to be one of the greateſt Emperours of the worlde.</p>
               <p>What was knowne of this countrie in former time was knowne vnder the name of <hi>Aethiopia:</hi> but the voyages of the Portingales in theſe late dayes haue beſt deſcribed it. The people therefore are Chriſtians: as is alſo their prince: but differing in many thinges from the Weſt Church: and in no ſorte acknowledging any ſupreme prerogatiue of the Biſhop of Rome. It is thought that they haue retayned chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, euen from the time of our Sauiour, being ſuppoſed to bee conuerted by the Chamberlaine of Candace the Queene of <hi>Aethiopia:</hi> who was inſtructed concerning Chriſt, by Phillip the Euang. in the <hi>Actes</hi> of the Apoſtes. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb.</hi> in his Eccleſiaſticall ſtorie doth make mention of this. But they doe to this day retaine Circumciſion: whereof the reaſon may be, that the Eunuch their conuerter not hauing any further conference with the Apoſtle, nor any elſe for him, did receiue the ceremonies of the Church vnperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, retaining Circumciſion: which among the Iewes was not aboliſhed, when he had conference with Phillip.</p>
               <p>Within the dominion of Preſter Iohn are the mountaines commonly called <hi>Lune montes,</hi> where is the firſt well-ſpring and ariſing of the riuer <hi>Nylus:</hi> which riuer running violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly along this countrie, and ſometimes haſtely increaſing by the melting of much ſnow from the mountaines, would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-run and drowne a great parte of <hi>Aegipt:</hi> but that it is ſlaked by many ponds, dams, &amp; ſluces, which are within the dominion of Preſter Iohn. And in reſpect hereof, for the maintenance of theſe, the Princes of <hi>Aegipt</hi> haue paid vnto the gouernor of <hi>Abiſſines</hi> a great tribute time out of minde: which of late the great Turke ſuppoſing to bee a cuſtome needeleſſe, did denye: till the people of the <hi>Abiſſines</hi> by commaundement of their Prince, did breake downe their dammes, and drowning <hi>Aegipt,</hi> did inforce the Turke to continue his paye, and to giue much money for the newe
<pb facs="tcp:26616:25"/>making of them very earneſtly, to his great charge, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a peace.</p>
               <p>There be other Countries in <hi>Africa,</hi> as <hi>Agiſimbae, Libiae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior, Nubia,</hi> and other of whome nothing is famous. But this may be ſaid of <hi>Africa</hi> in generall, that it bringeth forth ſtore of all ſortes of wilde beaſtes, as Elephants, Lyons, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Tigers, and the like: yea, according to the Prouerbe, <hi>Africa ſempor aliquid apportet noui.</hi> Oftentimes newe and ſtrange ſhapes of beaſtes are brought forth there. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof is, that the countrie being hot and full of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes which haue in them little water, the beaſtes of all ſortes are inforced to meete at thoſe fewe warring places that be, where oftentimes contrarie kindes haue coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the one with the other: ſo that there ariſeth newe kindes or ſpecies, which taketh parte of both. Such a one is the Leopard begotten of the Lyon, and the beaſt called Dardus, ſomewhat reſembling either of them. And thus fat of <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Inſulis ſeptentrionalibus.</head>
               <p>THe Ilands that doe lie in the North, are in number al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinite the chiefe of them onely ſhall be briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched. Very farre to the North, in the ſame clymate almoſt with Sweden that is vnder the very circle arctick, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Ireland,</hi> called in olde time <hi>Thule,</hi> which was then ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be the fartheſt parte of the worlde Northward, and and therefore is called by Virgill, <hi>Vltima Thule:</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie is colde, the people barbarous, and it yeeldeth little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie ſauing Hankes: in ſome parte of the yeare there is no night at all. Southward from thence lyeth Frizeland, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Latine <hi>Frizelandia,</hi> whereas the <hi>Frizeland</hi> ioyning to <hi>Germanie,</hi> is in Latine called <hi>Frizia.</hi> On the coaſt of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> one of the ſeuenteene prouinces is called <hi>Zeland,</hi> which containeth in it diuers Ilandes, in whome little is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, ſauing that in one of them is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſhing,</hi> or <hi>Firſhing,</hi> a
<pb facs="tcp:26616:25"/>towne of warre: and at <hi>Middleburg,</hi> in an other, a place of good marte. The States of the Lowe-countries doe holde this prouince vnited againſt the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Theſe Ilands haue bene much troubled of late with inundation of waters.</p>
               <p>The Iland that lyeth moſt Weſt of any fanie, is <hi>Ireland,</hi> which had in it heretofore many kings of their owne; but the whole land is now annexed vnto the crowne of <hi>England:</hi> The people naturally rude and ſuperſtitious; the countrie good and fruitefull: but that for want of tillage in diuers pleces, they ſuffer it to growe into bogges, and deſertes. That is true of this countrie (which <hi>Solmus</hi> writeth of ſome other) that ſerpents and adders doe not breede here; and in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> timber, of certaine experience, no ſpiders webbe is euer founde.</p>
               <p>The moſt renowned Iland in the worlde is <hi>Albion,</hi> or <hi>Britannia;</hi> which hath heretofore contained in it many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall kingdomes; but eſpecially in the time of the Saxons. It hath now in it the two kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> wherein are forue ſeuerall languages: that is, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, which the ciuill Scots doe barbarouſly ſpeake; the Welſh tongue, which is the language of the olde Britaines; the Corniſh, which is the proper ſpeech of <hi>Cornewall;</hi> and the Iriſh, which is ſpoken by thoſe Scots which liue on the Weſt parte of <hi>Scotland</hi> neare vnto <hi>Ireland.</hi> The commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of England, and pleaſures are well knowne vnto vs, and many of them may be expreſſed in this verſe:</p>
               <q>Anglia, Mons, Pons, Fons, Eccleſia, foemina, lana.</q>
               <p>This countrie, which in olde time was inhabited by the <hi>Britaines,</hi> was entered vpon by the Romaines, firſt vnder Iulius Caeſar, and was long by them kept in ſubiection but it was an error in them, when they wrote that England would breede nor keepe no Wolfe. It was afterwarde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne, and poſſeſſed by the Saxons: of whome, 7. kings
<pb facs="tcp:26616:26"/>at once did raigne here. After that the Danes out of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> did inuade it, and much moleſt it. And laſtly, vnder the leading of their Duke William, the <hi>Normans</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere it, and eſtabliſhed that gouernement, which to this day doth continue. And from whome, as from the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour our ordinarie computation is deriued. The <hi>Scots</hi> were in times paſt a moſt barbarous people, of whome <hi>Saint Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> reporteth: that he ſawe ſome of them in his time in France to feede on mans fleſh. They were neuer wholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by the Romaines.</p>
               <p>There be very many little Ilandes adioyning vnto the great Iland <hi>Britanie.</hi> As at the very North-point of <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>Orchades,</hi> which are in number aboue 30. The chiefe whereof, is named <hi>Orkney:</hi> where the people are barbarous,</p>
               <p>On the Weſt-ſide of <hi>Scotland</hi> towardes <hi>Ireland,</hi> lye the Ilandes called <hi>Hebreides:</hi> where inhabite the people ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily tearmed the Redſhankes. Not farre from thence, is the Ile <hi>Mona,</hi> commonly called <hi>The Ile of Man.</hi> The pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar iurisdiction of the Earles of Darbie, with homage not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding reſerued vnto the crowne of England.</p>
               <p>On the North-part of Wales, is the Iland of <hi>Angleſey:</hi> which is reputed a diſtinct ſhiere towardes France ſide: on the South part of England, is the Ile of <hi>Wight:</hi> in Latine cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vectis:</hi> which is a good holde in the narrowe ſeas againſt the French. More neare Fraunce, are the Iles of <hi>Garneſey,</hi> and <hi>Ierneſey,</hi> where they ſpeake French, and are vnder the crowne of England. There be alſo many other, but of ſmall accompt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Inſulis in Mari Mediterraneum.</head>
               <p>THere be many Ilandes in the <hi>Mediterran,</hi> renowmed in the olde writers: but the chiefe of them onely ſhall be touched. From the pillers of Hercules going Eaſtwarde, are two Ilands not farre from <hi>Spaine:</hi> which in times paſt
<pb facs="tcp:26616:26"/>were called <hi>Inſulae Baleares,</hi> for that the people oft then did vſe, both for their delight and armour, Slings which they continually almoſt carried aboute them. And whereunto, as Plinie writeth: they did traine vp their children from their yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt yeares. Not giuing them any meate, till they had from ſome Poſt or Beame caſt it downe with a ſling. Of theſe were thoſe Funditories, or Sling-caſters, which the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> did vſe in their warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romanes.</hi> The leſſer of theſe which lieth moſt Weſt, was called in olde time <hi>Minorica:</hi> and at this day <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norica.</hi> The bigger which lieth more Eaſt, was called <hi>Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica:</hi> and now <hi>Maiorica.</hi> They are both vnder the dominion of the King of Spaine.</p>
               <p>More Eaſtward in the ſea called <hi>Mare Inferum,</hi> or <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhenum,</hi> lieth the Iland of <hi>Corſica</hi> ouer againſt <hi>Genua,</hi> and direct Southward from thence, lyeth the great Iland <hi>Sardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> Forthe quiet poſſeſſing of which two, the warres were oftentimes reuiued betweene the olde <hi>Carthaginians</hi> and the <hi>Romanes.</hi> For theſe two Ilands lie in the middle very fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For both theſe are alſo at this day vnder the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And were the ſame which latelie the Cardinall of Lourain would perſwade the old king of Nauarre in France, that if hee woulde leaue his religion, and become a Papiſt, the Spaniſh king ſhould yeeld him either <hi>Sardinia,</hi> or at the loaſt <hi>Corſica,</hi> in recompence of <hi>Pampilona,</hi> and the reſt of the kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> which the Spaniards by force did detaine from him.</p>
               <p>Farther yet to the Eaſt, at the verie poynt of the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of <hi>Italy,</hi> lieth the great Iland of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> which ſome haue ſuppoſed to haue beene heretofore a part of the continent: but by an earth-quake and inundation of water, to haue bin rent off, and ſo made an Ileland. The figure of this Country, is <hi>Triquetra,</hi> or triangle three-ſquare.</p>
               <p>There was alſo great contention for the Countrie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> and the <hi>Romanes:</hi> but the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26616:27"/>obtayned it, and had from thence exceeding ſtore of corne yearelie: whereupon, <hi>Cicilie</hi> was called <hi>Horreum P. Romani.</hi> Here ſtoode the goodly citie called <hi>Siracuſa,</hi> which was deſtroyed and ſacked by Marcellus the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</p>
               <p>This was in times paſt a kingdom, where the two tyrants, the elder and the yonger <hi>Dioniſius</hi> did reigne: where Hiero alſo, that great friend to the <hi>Romanes</hi> did remaine. It was afterward made a prouince, and gouerned by a Praetor, or Deputie of the Romanes: whereof, Verres was one ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed againſt by Tullie. It grew afterwards to be a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againe: inſomuch, that Tancredus was King of <hi>Cici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> who went to the taking of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with Richard the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, king of England. Here was likewiſe Phalaris the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſo famous, king of <hi>Agrigentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Countrey is now alſo vnder the King of Spaine: who among other titles, calleth himſelfe king of both the <hi>Cicilies,</hi> reckoning this Iland for one, and that part of <hi>Italie</hi> for another, which is nowe called <hi>Calabria:</hi> and was in the Romane hyſtories named <hi>Maegna Graecia.</hi> There is nothing more renowmed in all <hi>Cicilia,</hi> either with the newe or olde writers, then the mountaine Aetna: which beeing on the out-ſide ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couered with ſnow, yet by a ſulphurie, or brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonie water, doth continuallie burne within: yea, ſo that whereas it was ſuppoſed in the ages laſt before vs, that the matter beeing conſumed, the fire had ceaſed: twiſe in our age it hath broke foorth againe, to the intollerable loſſe of all the Countrie adioyning: the aſhes thereof, deſtroying townes and fruites which were within the compaſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie myles about.</p>
               <p>This is that place whither Empedocles threwe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee might bee reputed a God. This is it whereof Virgill doth make his tract called Aenea, which the Poets did report to be the ſhop of Vulcan: where the <hi>Cyclops</hi> did frame the thunderbolts for Iupiter: and to conclude, this is
<pb facs="tcp:26616:27"/>it which ſome of our groſſe Papiſts haue not feared to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to be the place of Purgatorie.</p>
               <p>Not farre South from <hi>Cicilie,</hi> lieth the little Iland called in old time <hi>Melite,</hi> whence thoſe dogs come, which were ſo much deſired vnder the name of <hi>Canes Melitenſes.</hi> This is the countrie where S. Paul was caſt vp, after his ſhipwracke in his iourney to <hi>Rome:</hi> where the Viper hanged on his hand, and did not hurt him.</p>
               <p>This Countrie is now called <hi>Malta,</hi> and is one of the places moſt renowmed in the worlde, for the repelling of the Turkes: when Soliman the Emperour of them, did ſend agaynſt it a moſt mightie armie. It was then defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thoſe, who are called the knights of <hi>Malta:</hi> which by ſea, doe great ſpoile to the gallies of the Turke that paſſe that way.</p>
               <p>Neare vnto <hi>Graecia</hi> and <hi>Peloponneſus:</hi> on the Weſt-ſide toward <hi>Italie,</hi> is the Ile <hi>Corcyra,</hi> nowe tearmed <hi>Corfue:</hi> and not far South from that, is <hi>Cephalonia,</hi> and from thence South is <hi>Zant:</hi> called by Virgill <hi>Nemoriſa Zazinthus:</hi> all which Ilands haue beene heretofore vnder the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians:</hi> but are now vnder the Turke.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Zazinthus,</hi> our Engliſh marchants haue an houſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode for their trafique. Southeaſt from <hi>Morea,</hi> lieth the great Iland <hi>Creta,</hi> where Minos ſometime did raigne, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for his ſeueritie. This countrie was then called <hi>Heca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tompolis,</hi> as hauing in it an hundred townes and cities.</p>
               <p>The Turkes haue wonne this alſo long ſince from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians:</hi> it is now called <hi>Candie,</hi> from whence commeth our ordinarie ſugar of Candie. Betweene <hi>Creta</hi> and <hi>Pelopon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſus</hi> lieth <hi>Cythera,</hi> where was the fine Temple of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus:</hi> who thereof by the Poets, is called <hi>Cytherea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Ilandes are many, which doe lie in the ſea called <hi>Mare Aegeum,</hi> from the bottome of <hi>Greece,</hi> vnto the top of the Helliſpont: as all the <hi>Cyclades, Euboea,</hi> the great Iland <hi>Samos,</hi> and <hi>Chios,</hi> ſo <hi>Scyro,</hi> where Achilles was borne,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:28"/>and was king of that countrie. There was alſo <hi>Leſbos,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Metilene,</hi> and <hi>Ithaca,</hi> where Vliſſes was king, and <hi>Andros,</hi> whether Themiſtocles was ſent by the Athenia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for tribute: of which places, ſomething may be read in the olde hiſtorie of the Greekes: Diuers of theſe did ſtriue that Homer was borne in them: but of certaintie, many of thoſe kinges which Homer ſaith, came with Agamemnon to the ſiege of <hi>Troye:</hi> were kings but of theſe ſmall Ilands.</p>
               <p>Eaſtward from thence, not farre from ſome parte of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolia,</hi> or <hi>Aſia the leſſe,</hi> is the Iland <hi>Rhodus:</hi> the friendſhip of the inhabitants whereof, was in auntient time very much deſired by the Princes that had to doe that way. So that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander firſt, and the Romaines afterwardes did embrace their league.</p>
               <p>Here was that huge and mightie image of the Sunne, which was <hi>Choloſſus Rhodius,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This countrie was long defended by thoſe, who were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Knightes of the Rhodes, againſt the power of the Turke; and it was a great bulwarke, to defend Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: till that in the yeare one thouſand fiue hundred twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and two: Solimon the great Turke did winne it from the Chriſtians by force. From thence Southward, is the Ile of <hi>Carpathus:</hi> but in the farther end of the Eaſt parte of the <hi>Mediterraneum</hi> is <hi>Cyprus,</hi> which about 300. yeares ſince was a kingdome, &amp; did afforde great aide to the Chriſtians, that went to conquer the Holy land: but it is now vnder the Turke. The chiefe Citie thereof is <hi>Famaguſta,</hi> which is an Archbiſhoppes ſea: for Chriſtians for their tribute doe yet liue there. In this countrey in olde time was Venus much honoured, and thereof it was called <hi>Cypria,</hi> as alſo <hi>Paphia:</hi> becauſe ſhee had a Temple in a Citie there called <hi>Paphos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neare vnto <hi>Siria</hi> ſtood the Iland <hi>Tirus,</hi> againſt the pride whereof, the Prophets doe ſo much ſpeake. This was a rich citie for merchandiſe and nauigation in olde time, and
<pb facs="tcp:26616:28"/>is the place from whence <hi>Dido</hi> and the builders of <hi>Carthage</hi> did come.</p>
               <p>The deſtruction of it is moſt famous by Alexander the greate. Of the reſt of the ſmall Ilandes, wee doe ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De inſulis in Mare Indico.</head>
               <p>THe Ilandes are very many that doe lie in the ſeas ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning to the Eaſt Indies: but the moſt famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſhall be touched. Among the olde writers, as eſpecially appeareth by <hi>Solinis,</hi> was well knowne that which was then called <hi>Taprobana,</hi> which lieth vnder the Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall line. It was in that time a Maonarchy, where the Kings raigned, not by ſucceſſion, but by election: and if any of them did grow intollerable, he was depoſed, and inforced to die, with withdrawing from him all things neceſſary. This is nowe called <hi>Sumatra,</hi> and hath in it diuers Kings.</p>
               <p>Not far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence lye Eaſtward the two Ilandes called <hi>Iaua maior,</hi> and <hi>Iaua minor:</hi> which were alſo known to the olde writers, they haue alſo in them diuers Kings, as in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall may be noted, that all the Eaſt part, either in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, or in the Iland, haue very many ſmall Kinges and kingdomes. From thence yet more Eaſt, lieth a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Iles, which are now called the <hi>Moluccoes,</hi> which are places as rich for their quantity as anie in the world. From theſe it is, that the Spaniards haue yearely ſo greate quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all kindes of ſpice: neither is there any place of all the Eaſt Indies that do more richly furniſh home their caractes then do theſe Moluccoes.</p>
               <p>Some of theſe Ilandes, the Spaniards haue gotte into their owne poſſeſſion: with the Kings of ſome other they haue league: and a third ſorte vtterly deteſt them. More North-ward ouer againſt China, lieth a greate Iland called <hi>Iapona</hi> or <hi>Iapan:</hi> the people whereof, are much of the ſame nature with the men of China. This countrey was firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered
<pb facs="tcp:26616:29"/>by the Ieſuites, who in a blinde zeale haue trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto the fartheſt partes of the worlde, to winne men to their religion; this Ilande is thought to bee very rich. The reſt that bee either neare vnto <hi>Aſia,</hi> or vnto <hi>Africa,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is little written of them we paſſe ouer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Inſulis in Mari Atlantico.</head>
               <p>THere bee many Ilands which lie Weſt-ward from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> and from <hi>Europe,</hi> as thoſe which are called the <hi>Gorgades,</hi> that lie in the ſame climate with Guinea, which are foure in number: but not inhabited by men: but they are full of Goates. North-ward from thence in the ſame cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with the South-parte of Marocco, lie thoſe which are called <hi>Canariae,</hi> or the fortunate Ilandes, which are ſeuen in nomber, being moſt fruitfull and very pleaſant: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called by that name. This is famous in them that it hath pleaſed all Coſmographers to make their Meridiane to be the firſt poynte where they doe beginne to reckon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of their longitude, and vnto them after three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore degrees, to returne againe. From theſe Ilandes it is that thoſe ſtrong and pleaſant ſackes which are called Canari wines are brought, and from thence are fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thoſe which they call Canarie Birdes: theſe Ilandes are vnder the Crowne of Spaine.</p>
               <p>More Northward from thence, lye theſe Ilandes which are called <hi>Azotes inſulae,</hi> being ſixe or ſeuen in number: of which <hi>Tercera</hi> is one of the chiefe: of whome, the reſt by ſome are called the <hi>Terceraes,</hi> which are farre inferiour in fruitfulneſſe vnto the Canaries, theſe were firſt vnder the Crowne of Portugale: and one of them was the laſt which was kept out from the King of Spaine by the <hi>Prior don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio:</hi> who now calleth himſelfe King of Portugale: but the Spaniard at the laſt tooke this <hi>Tercera</hi> from him, and doeth poſſeſſe all theſe Ilandes tagether with the reſt of the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which did belong to the Portingale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26616:29"/>
               <head>De America ſiue Orbe nouo.</head>
               <p>ALthough ſome diſpute out of Plato, and the olde wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that there was not onely a geſſe, but a kinde of knowledge in auntient time, that beſides <hi>Europia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa:</hi> there was another large countrey lying to the Weſt, yet he that ſhall aduiſedly vſe the coniectures made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, may ſee that there is nothing of ſufficiencie to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force any ſuch knowledge; but that all antiquitie was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignorant of the newe founde countries towarde the Weſt: whereunto this one argument moſt forcible may giue credite: that at the firſt ariuing of the Spaniards there, they founde in thoſe partes nothing ſhewing trafique or knowledge of any other Nation: but the people naked, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuill, ſome of them deuourers of mans fleſh, ignorant of ſhipping, without all kinde of learning, hauing no remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of hiſtorie or writing among them, neuer hauing heard of any ſuch religion as in other places of the world is knowne: but being vtterly ignorant of Scripture, or Chriſt, or Moyſes, or any God: neither hauing among them any token of croſſe, Church, Temple, or deuotion, agreeing with other Nations.</p>
               <p>God therefore remembring the prophecie of his ſonne, that the Goſpell of the kingdome ſhould before the day of iudgement be preached in all coaſtes and quarters of the worlde: and in his mercie intending to free the people, or at the leaſt ſome fewe of them from the bondage of Sathan: who did detaine them in blockiſh ignoraunce, and from their Idolatrous ſeruice, vnto certaine vile ſpirites, whome they called their <hi>Zemes,</hi> and moſt obſequiouſly did adore them: and raiſed vp the ſpirit of a man worthie of perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all memorie: one <hi>Chriſtophorus Columbus,</hi> borne at <hi>Genua</hi> in <hi>Italie,</hi> to ſet his minde to the diſcouery of a new worlde, Who finding by that compaſſe of the olde knowne worlde, that there muſt needes bee a much more mightie ſpace, which the ſun by his dayly motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did compaſſe aboute, then
<pb facs="tcp:26616:30"/>that which was alreadie knowne and diſcouered: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that this huge quantitie, might as well by land as ſea, could neuer ſatisfie himſelfe, till that hee might attempt to make proofe of the veritie thereof.</p>
               <p>Being therefore himſelfe a priuate man, and of more ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue then abilitie. After his reaſons and demonſtrations layd downe: whereby hee might enduce men, that it was no vaine thing which he went about. Hee went vnto many of the Princes of Chriſtendome: and among other, vnto Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the ſeuenth, then King of England: deſiring to bee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſhipping and men fitte for ſuch a nauigation. But theſe men refuſing him: parly, becauſe they gaue no credite vnto his newe narration: and partly, leaſt they ſhould be derided by their neighbour Princes, if by this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noway ſtranger they ſhould be couſoned: but eſpeciallie, for that they were vnwilling to ſuſtaine the charges of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. At laſt hee betaketh himſelfe vnto the court of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinandus and Elizabeth King and Queene of <hi>Caſtile:</hi> where alſo at the firſt, hee ſound but colde entertainment: yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in his purpoſe without wearineſſe, and with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie: it pleaſed God to moue the minde of Elizabeth the Queene, to deale with her husbande to furniſh him foorth two ſhippes for the diſcouerie onely, and not for conqueſt. Whereupon, Columbus in the yeare 1492. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with his brother Bartholomeus Columbus, and manie Spaniards: ſayled farre to the Weſt, for the ſpace of three ſcore dayes and more, with the great indignation and often mutinies of his companie: fearing that by reaſon of their long diſtance from home, they ſhould neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe. In ſo much, that the generall, after many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of them to goe forwarde, was at length enforced to craue but three dayes: wherein, if they ſawe not land, he promiſed to returne; and God did ſo bleſſe him, to the end that this voyage might not prooue in vaine, that in that ſpace, one of his companie did eſpie fire: which was a
<pb facs="tcp:26616:30"/>certaine arguments that they were neare to the land, as it ſell out in deede. The firſt land whereunto they came was an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, called by the enhabitants <hi>Haity.</hi> But in remembrance of <hi>Spaine</hi> from whence he came: he tearmed it <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and finding it to bee a countrie full of pleaſure, and hauing in it aboundaunce of gold and pearle, he proceeded farther, and diſcouered another bigge Ile which is called <hi>Cuba,</hi> of the which beeing verie glad, with great treaſure, hee retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Spaine, bringing ioyfull newes of his happie ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards who by nature are a people proude, haue ſince the death of Columbus, laboured to obſcure his fame, enuying that an Italian or ſtranger ſhould be reported to be the firſt diſcouerer of thoſe parts, and therefore haue in their writings ſince giuen forth: that there was a Spaniard which had firſt beene there, and that Columbus meeting with his cards and deſcriptions, did but purſue his enterpriſe, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the glorie to himſelfe. But this fable of theirs doth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the ſame ſpirite, wherewithall many of them in his life time did reproach him, that it was no matter of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to find out theſe countries: but that if he had not done it, many other might, and would: which being ſpoken to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbus at a ſolemne dinner, he called for an egge, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the gueſts one after another to ſet it vp on end, which when they could not do, he gently bruiſing the one ende of it, did make it flat, and ſo ſet it vp: by imitation whereof, each of the other did the ſame: whereby he mildlie did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach their enuie toward him, and ſhewed how eaſie it was to do that which a man had ſeene done before him. To go forward therefore, Columbus being returned to Caſtile, after his welcome to the Princes, was made great Admirall of Spaine, and with a new fleete of more ſhippes, was ſent to ſearch farther, which he accordingly did, and quickly found the maine land, not farre off from the Tropicke of <hi>Cancer,</hi> which part of the countrie, in honour of Spaine, hee called
<pb facs="tcp:26616:31"/>
                  <hi>Hispania noua,</hi> and in reſpect whereof at this day the King of Spaine doth entitle himſelfe <hi>Hiſpaniaram Rex.</hi> They found the people both of the maine land and Ilandes verie exceeding in number: naked without cloathes or armour: ſowing no corne, but making their breade of a kinde of roote which they call Maies. Men moſt ignorant of all kinde of learning: admiring the Chriſtians as if they had beene ſent downe from heauen, and thinking them to be immortall: wondering at their Shippes, and the tacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereof: for they had no ſhippes of their owne: but bigge troughes which they call their Canoaes: beeing made hollowe of the bodie of one Tree, with the ſharpe bones of fiſhes: for iron, or ſuch like inſtruments they haue none.</p>
               <p>The Spaniardes did here finde the people to bee moſt ſimple, without fraude, giuing them kinde entertainement according to their beſt manner, exchanging for kniues, glaſſes, and ſuch like toyes, great aboundance of golde and pearle.</p>
               <p>The deſire whereof, cauſed the Spaniards to ſeeke far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the countries: but the tyrannie and couetouſneſſe of the Spariards was ſuch, in taking from them their goods, in deflouring their wiues and daughters: but eſpecially, in forcing them to labour in their golde mines without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as if they had beene beaſts: that the people dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them, and the name of Chriſtians for their ſakes, did ſome of them kill themſelues, and the mothers deſtroyed their children in their bellies, that they might not be borne to ſerue ſo hatefull a Nation: and ſome of them did in warre conſpire againſt them: ſo that by ſlaughter and otherwiſe, the people of the countrie are almoſt all waſted nowe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an hundred yeeres, beeing before many millions: thoſe which remaine are as ſlaues, and the Spaniards almoſt onely doe inhabit thoſe parts.</p>
               <p>By reaſon that the countrie is exceeding rich and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:26616:31"/>the Spaniards with great deſire did ſpreade themſelues toward the North, where they founde more reſiſtance: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though nothing in compariſon of warriours: but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of their labour was, for to conquere the kingdome of <hi>Mexico:</hi> which <hi>Mexico,</hi> is a Citie verie great and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, as almoſt any in the worlde, ſtanding in the midſt of a great mariſh or fenne. The conquerour of this, was Ferdinandus Corteſius, ſo much renowmed in Spaine vnto this day.</p>
               <p>In the ſea coaſtes of all this <hi>Noua Hiſpania</hi> the Kings of Spaine haue built many townes, and Caſtles, and therein haue erected diuerſe fornaces and forges, for the trying and ſining of their golde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De partibus Americae verſus Septentrionem.</head>
               <p>THe rumour of the diſcouerie of theſe partes beeing blowne ouer Chriſtendome: and the great quantitie of the land, together with the fruitfulneſſe thereof, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported abroad, ſome other Nation did enterpriſe to ſet foot therein: as namely the Frenchmen, who ſent certaine ſhips vnto a part of this counttie, lying North from <hi>Hiſpania noua,</hi> ſome fewe degrees without the Tropicke of <hi>Cancer:</hi> into which when they had ariued becauſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ground, and trees, as if it had beene a perpetuall ſpring, they called it <hi>Florida;</hi> where after ſome fewe of them had for a time ſetled themſelues, the Spaniards tooke notice of it, and being vnwilling to endure any ſuch neighbours, they came ſuddainlie on them, and moſt cruelly ſlue them all, without taking any ranſome, yet the Spaniards for want of men are not able to inhabit that countries, but leaue it to the olde people.</p>
               <p>The Engliſhmen alſo deſirous by nauigation to adde
<pb facs="tcp:26616:32"/>ſomething vnto their owne countrie, as before time they had trauailed toward the fartheſt North part of <hi>America,</hi> ſo lately finding that part which lieth betweene <hi>Florida,</hi> and <hi>Noua Francia,</hi> was not inhabited by any Chriſtians, and was a land verie fruitfull and fit to plant in, they ſent thither two ſeuerall times, two ſeuerall companies, as Colonies to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit that part, which in remembrance of the virginity of their Queene, they named <hi>Virginia.</hi> But this voyage beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed on the charge of priuate men: and not thorowlie being followed by the State: the poſſeſſion of this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia</hi> is nowe diſcontinued, and the countrie at this preſent left to the old inhabitants.</p>
               <p>Northward from thence on the ſea-coaſt, lieth <hi>Norom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bega,</hi> which is the South-parte of that which the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did without diſturbance of any Chriſtian for a time poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>For the French-men did diſcouer a large part of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> on toward the circle Arctick, and did build there ſome townes, and named it of their owne countrie, <hi>Noua Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Enliſh-men about the yeare 1570. did aduenture farre, for to open the North partes of <hi>America,</hi> and ſayled as farre as the very circle Arcticke, hoping for to haue found a paſſage by the North to the <hi>Moluccos,</hi> and to <hi>China,</hi> which hitherto, neither by the North of <hi>Aſia,</hi> nor by the North of <hi>America,</hi> could bee effected by them, by reaſon of the verie great colde and yſe in that clymate. The reſt of the inland beeing an huge ſpace of earth, hath not hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by any Chriſtian to any purpoſe beene diſcouered: but by thoſe neare the ſea-coaſts it may bee gathered, that they all which doe there inhabite: are men rude and vnciuill, without knowledge of God. Yet on the North-weſt part of <hi>America,</hi> ſome of our Engliſh-men going through the ſtraightes of <hi>Magellan,</hi> and paſſing toward the North by <hi>Hiſpania noua,</hi> haue touched on a Countrie where they
<pb facs="tcp:26616:32"/>found good entertainement: the King thereof yeelding himſelfe to the ſubiection of the Queene of England: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they tearmed it <hi>Noua Albion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>De Peru &amp; Braſilia.</head>
               <p>WHen the Portingales had firſt begun their nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by <hi>Africa</hi> vnto the Eaſt Indies; ſome of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to haue helde their courſe Eaſtwarde vnto <hi>Caput bone ſpei,</hi> were driuen ſo farre Weſt-ward by tempeſt, that they landed in a large and great countrey, which by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name, is called <hi>Braſilia:</hi> where they began to enter trafique, and with Townes and Caſtles to plant themſelues, before that the Spaniardes had diſcouered <hi>Peru,</hi> which is the South parte of <hi>America.</hi> So that at this day, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the King of Spaine hath in <hi>Braſilia,</hi> it is in right of the crowne of Portingale. The countrie is large, hauing in it many people and ſeuerall kingdomes which are not all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the Portingals: but ſo, that other Chriſtians, as namely the Frenchmen, being driuen out of their countrie for religion, haue ſet footing there: though afterwardes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine they haue abandoned it.</p>
               <p>The inhabitants hereof, are men alſo vtterly vnlearned, but men more ingenious then the common ſorte of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericans:</hi> goodly of bodie, and ſtraight of proportion, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes naked, reaſonable good warriours after their countrie faſhion; vſing to fat ſuch enemies as they take in the warres, that afterwardes they may deuoure them, which they doe with great pleaſure. For diuers of the people of theſe quarters, as the Caribles and the Canibals are all ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of mans fleſh, In this countrie groweth aboundance of that wood, which ſince is brought into <hi>Europe</hi> for to dye red colours, and is of the place whence it commeth, called <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zil-wood,</hi> the trees whereof are exceeding great.</p>
               <p>After that the Spaniardes had for a time poſſeſſed <hi>Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia noua,</hi> for the deſire of gold and pearle, ſome of them tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled
<pb facs="tcp:26616:33"/>towardes the South. And as by water they found that ſea Weſtward from <hi>Peru</hi> (which is alwayes very calme, and is by them called the South-ſea, as the other wherein <hi>Cuba</hi> ſtandeth, is termed the North-ſea) ſo by land, they founde that huge &amp; mightie countrie which is named <hi>Peru:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the people are for the moſt parte very barbarous, and without God, men of great ſtature; yea, ſome of them farre higher then the ordinarie ſorte of men in France, vſing to ſhoote ſtrongly with bowes made of fiſhe bones, and moſt cruell people to their enemies. Among theſe, the Spaniards partly by force, but eſpecially by perfidious treaſon, did get infinite ſummes of golde and pearle: wherein being allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and hoping for more (by reaſon that a great parte here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lyeth vnder the <hi>Zona Torrida</hi>) They haue heare and there ſcatteringly vpon the ſea-coaſtes, ſet vp ſome Townes and Caſtles; but are not able to poſſeſſe almoſt any thing of the land: neither haue they as yet diſcouered the inwarde partes thereof. Some of theſe Spaniardes deſirous for to ſee how farre this land of <hi>Peru</hi> did goe towardes the South, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled downe till at length they founde the landes end, and a little ſtraight or narrowe ſea: which did runne from the maine <hi>Ocean</hi> towardes <hi>Africa</hi> into the South ſea. One ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelanus was he that found this ſtraight, and (although it be dangerous) paſſed thorowe it: ſo that of his name, it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Fretum Magelanicum,</hi> or Magelanes ſtraightes. And this is the way whereby, as the Spaniards doe paſſe to the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of <hi>Peru,</hi> and <hi>Hiſpania noza,</hi> ſo, whoſoeuer will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the whole worlde (as ſome of our Engliſh haue done) He muſt of neceſſitie, for any thing that is yet knowne, paſſe thorowe this narrowe ſtraight.</p>
               <p>Magellanus did finde on the other ſide towards the Pole, the maine continent: which alſo the Portingales in their voyages to the Eaſt <hi>Indies</hi> haue ſometimes bene driuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: whereof nothing is diſcouered, but that in one place they did ſee aboundance of Parats, and greater then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:
<pb facs="tcp:26616:33"/>whereof they did call it <hi>Pſittacorum regio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is thought to be a mightie huge countrie, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in compaſſe all the degrees of longitude, in the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent thereof, and is ſuppoſed to goe vnto the South pole: By reaſon that no ſea is yet founde to breake in, or breake through the ſame.</p>
               <p>There be alſo deſcribed by ſome of our late writers, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine great Landes towardes the North-pole. And our Engliſh-men in their Nauigations haue touched <hi>Gronland:</hi> but the nature of them, and whether they be ſuch, and ſo many as is reported, is not certainely knowne.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
